[music]
>> Good evening, good day everybody and
welcome back to the Ask Abhijit Show. I
hope you're all doing great.
Um today we're going to take questions
about absolutely anything you want. I'll
take questions primarily from the super
chat. If there is more time, I'll take
questions from the regular chat as well.
Um the time duration is about 2 hours,
but but let's see. Maybe it will extend
beyond that. I'll
make sure that I take as many questions
as is possible in this time period. Now,
let's see who all is there on the live
chat with us.
Pranav [snorts] 561 Om Bekikar, hello,
good to see you.
Uh Amisha Mishra is here. Maclevin 69,
good to see you as well. MAK
I am Dib
Nike Shailesh is here from Pune,
Maharashtra. Good evening. Ram Ram ji.
Sky Prime
Yulakh Yuber, okay, whatever that is.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh Maulana Abhijit Charu, what on earth
is what kind of name is that?
Um uh
anyway, from Kalinga Pranav 581 Dragon
Slayer Vansh Gada Animish Bharatiya,
namaste.
Vansh Gada is coming after a long time.
Well, good to have you back, Vansh Gada
ji.
Uh Bala from Washi is here. Vikash PJ
Animals from Lab Animals for Laugh is
here. From Mumbai, is this red a little
bit too red?
Maybe we can make it a little less red.
Okay.
Uh Nike Shailesh is here also. Animish
Abhyuday Singh, namaskar. Rudra Avatar,
well, thank you.
Namaskar. Starlord is here. Daryl is
here from Jaipur.
Uh
Animish once again. Mystic SK Jai Shri
Krishna. Ayush Singh good to see you.
South Lucknow.
Youmix Glo Haha. Rishabh Dang.
Um
Who else do we have? Uh
Gajapati Dave Maclevin once again.
Priyanka Jawalia, good evening. Pranam.
Uh Real Vladimir Putin.
VSVS, hello, hello. Uh Boruto Uchiha,
namaste arigato.
Ankita Kachhap, good evening. SHSJ
is here from Alaknanda Galaxy.
Uh VSVS once again.
And everyone else. Critical Thinker is
here from Mars. Okay. Lol Manu is here
from Chhattisgarh.
Dragon Slayer once again. And everyone
else. Okay, let's get going with some
questions. Let's let's um Have I seen
Doronder? Not yet. I haven't had time to
see it, but I will watch the movie.
Parth Prajapati is here from Japan.
>> [clears throat]
>> Prayas is here from Moscow. Moscow.
And all right. So
Sahil Patil is marking attendance.
Hello. Maclevin is saying, have you seen
Doronder? I haven't seen it yet, but I
do plan to see it as soon as possible at
the earliest possible opportunity.
Ananta Subramanian, hello.
Parth Nonis here from Washi. Omkar
Shinde Hriday Das Sahil Patil Brave
Robot Meow.
Uh Diva Dainik Hi Name Viva, hello.
Okay. Uh let's take some questions. What
questions do we have? Parth Non says
can India's littering problem be solved
by the fund system?
What were the ambitions of the Nazis?
Why it's spreading Indians in my
opinion? Cheating isn't the culture.
Okay, like three government questions do
we have? One, two, three questions.
What's a fund system?
Is it something German? Is it that
German self-service kind of thing? Let's
quickly find out what is a fund system.
Um P F A N D. Sounds very German. Fund.
Self-service, is it
fund?
Deposit deposit refund system, etc.
Look, the question you're asking is
what's the solution to India's littering
problem? The solution to India's
littering problem is not fancy technol
technology.
Technology is not the solution. Before
Germany had the fund system, before they
had the all these technological means
they still did not have a littering
problem.
You can introduce as much technology as
you want in India, but you will not
solve the littering problem unless you
solve the deeper issue the root cause of
the problem. See, in India there's this
problem, right?
There there's a major massive huge
gigantic problem in India. What is the
problem?
It's what nobody wants to speak about.
You will have government servants with a
salary of 30, 40,000 rupees a month
3 lakhs, 4 lakhs rupees a year who will
have huge bungalows.
Everyone knows that.
Right?
You have all these public works that
happen every year in various cities in
India. Every year they dig up the roads.
Every year they lay a new road. In 6
months the road is again crumbled up.
Again they will dig up the road. What is
all this?
It's corruption.
The entire system looks like allegedly,
hypothetically is geared towards
corruption.
Whatever money huge amounts of money is
allocated every year to various budgets.
And where does most of the money go?
If you have the situation
nothing is going to be solved.
You will have you know, you'll have
dustbins or or trash bins which are not
collected from. Some places you don't
even have trash bins so people love to
litter.
And you know, people
when they see that the system is working
against them
This is when they see the system is so
unfair where people get do no work
but earn so much money, then people get
demoralized and they stop following the
rules.
Right?
So what is the solution? The solution is
a clean up.
Not of the littering problem first.
But of the deep defects and deficiencies
in our system.
Once that is solved, once you solve the
corruption problem enforcement of the
rules will be will be done properly.
Right now there is no enforcement of the
rules. No one cares.
Every day these days you know, 6 months
ago people were
talking about pigeons are a menace to
India. Now stray dogs are a menace to
India. This thing is they'll keep
talking about it, but because of the
incredible inefficiency of the Indian
system, nothing will be done about this.
The only thing that's preventing a
genocide of of of dogs in India is the
incredible inefficiency of the Indian
system that doesn't care about what
needs to be done.
All it's it's all about slogan slogan
slogan slogans.
Slogans and and headlines and all that.
And and sound bites.
But everyone knows what's happening.
Every Indian knows what actually is
happening. Right? It's all about
slogans. It's all about performative
you know performative little bit of
actions. That's it.
So that is the root cause of all the
problems in India.
The moment you clean up the system, the
littering and every problem in India
will be dealt with with an iron hand.
That's the issue. All right? So yeah,
Nazi ambitions, it's a big big topic. We
know they wanted to conquer the world.
They want to avenge the humiliation of
the First World War. Yeah?
Why it's spreading Indians?
Nothing to do with me.
Okay, next. Bhaskar Bandit says Thailand
versus Cambodia.
Uh due to conflict due to the Shiva
temple. No, it's not because of the
Shiva temple, sir. Before that, uh
Sandeep Sandeep Darwar, well, becomes a
YouTube member. Well, thank you so much.
And welcome to the membership. And thank
you so much.
Okay, Bhaskar Bandit says Thailand
versus Cambodia conflict due to the
Shiva temple. It's not due to the Shiva
temple. That is not the cause of the
conflict.
The Shiva temple is a symptom of of what
has gone wrong.
The the conflict is not
The temple is not the cause of the
conflict. Okay, let I'll explain what it
is. New possible proxy war loading
between communists versus freedom and
democracy. What freedom? What democracy?
There's no freedom democracy anywhere in
the world. It's it's all an illusion.
Uh interestingly the new the temple
complex is situation is situated on a
400 meter cliff. Okay, now what's what's
the deal?
Let us understand what this conflict is
about. Now I have I had this this series
called Geostrategy
in which I have spoken about this. But
maybe you know, YouTube has curtailed
the reach. Maybe nobody watched it.
Uh whatever. Let me explain again to
those of you who are watching now and
those of you who will watch um when
after this is live.
See, first of all this this temple, the
Preah Vihear temple
it it was built mo
The construction started more than a
thousand years ago.
Uh it was one of the Khmer kings.
Suryavarman first or second or somebody.
You can look up the names.
It was a Khmer king who built it.
And the temple is dedicated to Lord
Shiva, of course.
And it's an interesting temple. It's
laid out in a north-south
alignment instead of an east-west
alignment that is typical of other
temples in the region.
Uh we can even look it up, but I'll just
explain.
So, that's what the temple is. It's a
very ancient temple. It's a Khmer era
temple. 1,000 years ago it was built.
Now, why is there a dispute about this?
That's the real matter that we have to
discuss. It's It's uh Obviously both
nations, Thailand and Cambodia, deeply
desire ownership over this temple
because it's
part of part of their ancient ancient
culture. Deeply revered temple even
though nobody worships today because of
the situation there.
Now, in the 1860s,
okay?
In the 1860s, Thailand became a vassal
of the French.
And
even Cambodia became a vassal
of the French. So, there was French
colonization
in this region. Uh the the king of
Cambodia at the time was Prince was King
Norodom Norodom Norodom.
And
so, there is French colonization in the
19th century in the region in Southeast
Asia in what they call Indochina,
Thailand, Cambodia, Vietnam, that area,
okay? Now, in the early 1900s, maybe
1906, 1907, around that time,
maps are commissioned.
The government of Thailand, which is
under the French,
it commissions it it asks the French
government
to do a survey in the region, a
geographical survey, topographical
survey,
and uh
and create maps of the region.
Okay? Now, at that time,
the the
the border between Thailand and
Cambodia, the two kingdoms, was defined
in such a way
that the Preah Vihear temple was on the
Thai side of the border.
Okay?
It was on the Thai side of the border.
It was not on the Cambodian side of the
border. For Since the 1800s, mid-1800s,
the Preah Vihear temple was on the Thai
side of the border.
Now, in the early 1900s, 1906, 1907, the
French government made a bunch of maps,
maybe 10, 11 maps of the region.
>> [clears throat]
>> And these maps were then
used by the government of Thailand for
various purposes, okay? Officially.
And out of these 10, 11 maps, one of the
maps produced by the French government
showed the temple
on the Cambodian side of the border.
And the Thai government, for whatever
reason, continued using these maps.
They did not protest.
What is the reason for that? I'm not
sure. Maybe they were scared of the
French government. Maybe the French
government was too powerful. Maybe
France was too powerful. Thai Thailand
was a vassal. Whatever the situation
was, they did not protest and they kept
on using this these maps in an official
capacity.
Now, in the Second World War, Thailand
was on the side of Japan.
Very bad, very naughty.
Yes? If you're on the side of Japan,
you're very bad, very evil. So, Thailand
was on the side of Japan
in the Second World War. Japan lost.
And in 1946 or something, there was an
agreement in Washington or something
in which the Preah Vihear temple was
given to Cambodia officially on the
maps.
And Thailand had not protested the 1907,
1908, whatever year it was that that
map, those that one map. So, it was said
that now it's part of Cambodia because
you have not protested for 40 years or
50 years or whatever.
So, it becomes part of Cambodia. Then in
the 1960s or something, uh
uh
it is
the Preah Vihear temple is declared a
UNESCO World Heritage Site. Not
declared, but it's There are some moves
towards that. The World Heritage Sites
started off in the '60s or '70s or
something. So, around that time, uh when
um
this becomes a thing in the UNESCO World
Heritage
Site status thing, that's when the
dispute flares up again.
And Thailand uh protests. It says that
this should be our territory. And that's
where the protest that's where the issue
becomes uh open again.
And in 20
2008 or something, there was a big
flare-up. Maybe it was then that the
UNESCO World Heritage status was given
or whatever, but there was a bunch There
was there was some protest by Thailand
in the 1960s or '70s. And then there was
a major escalation of the conflict, you
know, hot conflict, military conflict in
2008. Several soldiers died on both
sides, etc.
And then the International Court of
Justice comes into the picture and they
said that this this should be with
Cambodia and then the
the conflict simmers down. And now it
has again simmered up again. Not
simmered up, it's flared up again. It's
gone to hot war
scenario
a couple of times this year. Right now
it's again hot.
And Donald Trump apparently had ended
that war, but it started again. Now,
apparently he's trying to end it again.
Let's see how it goes. But the issue
What is the root cause? The root cause
is foreign meddling in the region.
And today
Thailand is the much more powerful
nation.
And Cambodia is militarily much weaker.
But this conflict is simmering and
Thailand is not
given uh
the go-ahead to take the temple through
military means.
Even though it was on the Thai side of
the border in
in the 19th century, etc.
So, this is an artificially created
conflict. It is It has been created by
foreigners drawing lines on maps.
Okay? And then arbitrarily putting one
thing on one side and after a few months
they put it on the other side. That sort
of nonsense. These The Europeans are
responsible for most of the conflicts
that that exist in the world.
It is their legacy.
Now, who's that? Who's wrong?
I I don't know. The It was a Khmer
temple.
The Khmers were Cambodian. Well, from
today's perspective, the Khmers
were
were based in Cambodia. Angkor Wat,
where is it?
Cambodia, right? Not Thailand.
But it's the same culture. It's the same
civilization. It's our civilization.
It's our culture.
So, I think who should mediate? Should
Donald Trump mediate? Who the hell is he
to mediate?
He's an outsider.
I think the only nation that actually
can mediate in this in this matter is
India. But India is a secular nation.
We are secular.
So, we will just urge the both both the
parties to to to not fight. Please don't
fight. Please negotiate, blah blah blah.
India has still not reached that that's
that stature.
India still doesn't have the
civilizational confidence as of today
to to you know,
put itself
forward and say that let let me
end this war for you in in a proper way.
So, what is the resolution? Well,
both sides want it.
Maybe both sides should govern it. Maybe
that should be the resolution.
It's not an India-Pakistan situation
where you have two sides that you know,
two nations, artificial one one
artificial one one not, and both you
know, one side wants to kill the other.
Cambodia doesn't want to kill Thailand.
And Thailand doesn't want to kill kill
Cambodia. They just both desire this
temple. Maybe there should be some kind
of joint sovereignty or something in a
way that is
dignified for both sides. Something like
that needs to happen because anyway it
is shared culture, shared shared
heritage, shared civilization.
Um but there may be a geopolitical angle
to this. Cambodia is more aligned with
China and Thailand has been
well, let us say
aligned with the US
since the end of the Second World War.
So, maybe there is something to do with
that. Maybe the United States wants this
entire region to be destabilized. Maybe
to keep China on the back foot. And next
to
Thailand, north of Thailand, we have
Burma where there is more
destabilization happening which is
spilling over into India in Manipur.
So, this entire region, maybe in the
coming years, will be more and more
destabilized because of external
forces, because of
major powers that want to destabilize
the region for local powers. region.
Okay.
Bhaskar Bandit says, "Privet. Privet.
How is Moscow?
I'm sure the weather is cold." Um
"Ancient Bharat had better civic sense
than today due to monarchy enforcement,
but how did investigations happen of
murder, theft, littering, etc. in the
absence of today's technology?" Well, we
have no idea.
You see, we can only
comment about these matters,
investigations of murder, theft,
littering, whatever.
We can speak about this only if we still
have official documents from that time.
Investigation documents, court
proceedings, we have none of that. What
happened to all of that? Everything was
burned down. Everything was destroyed.
Right?
I'm talking about pre-
occupation
Bharat.
Bharat from before 1000 AD.
None of the records from those times
survived. The only thing that survives
are inscriptions on temple temple walls,
inscriptions on you know, rock
inscriptions, Ashoka's inscriptions, uh
copper plate grants that have survived
somehow.
But none of the paper parchment None of
that has survived. Some some, you know,
some birch bark records, etc. No, lots
actually survived in temples that were
not destroyed. But those are all
religious, philosophical, etc. texts.
But texts related to official
proceedings,
government proceedings, those would have
been in in maybe in government
buildings, etc. Those were all destroyed
and you know, we don't have any of that.
For example, we do have some court
proceedings,
records of court proceedings that are
still available from Egypt, ancient
Egypt. Um those were inscribed on on
papyrus, uh you know, on the medium of
medium called papyrus.
Uh so, some of that is available. In the
case of Mesopotamia, we have the world's
oldest customer complaint um in which
the the the the villain was a merchant
called Ea-nasir who gave bad who sold
who delivered
you know
uh low quality copper ore. So, wherever
records have survived in various parts
of the world, we have some understanding
some idea of how things were done. Uh
when it comes to England, we have
copious evidence of court proceedings
and all that because of which we're able
to draw a very detailed uh
um
we are able to understand the history in
great detail.
But in case of India, everything has
been destroyed. The foreigners, the
Turks, they burnt all the libraries. So,
all of that got destroyed and we have no
idea how these things were done. But
obviously, these things happen, okay?
Investigations happen, obviously. We had
very high-quality governance.
We had very high-quality administrative
uh systems in India.
Whether it is the Mauryan period or the
Gupta period or the Kushan period or
even the Satavahana period or whatever.
We had very high-quality governance
systems in India.
Very sophisticated governance. So,
clearly this doesn't work. High-quality
governance will not exist without
high-quality judiciary, high-quality
police,
all you know, records being kept, etc.
But the all the records are gone. So,
can't answer the question
because none of the records exist today.
They've destroyed everything.
And that's something we Indians need to
realize.
What kind of damage has been done to our
civilization?
We don't have the records of the past.
Everything was destroyed. Everything was
burnt because they hated our culture and
civilization.
When when you go to England, you can
read
court proceedings and and official
records and diplomatic correspondence
from the 1600s and the 1400s. We even
have the Magna Carta from uh the time of
William the Conqueror,
the Domesday Book, the Bayeux Tapestry.
We have so many things.
You can actually, you know, get a get a
week-by-week, month-by-month
understanding of history based on
official documents from the Crown's
uh records in England. We should have
had the same thing for India.
Imagine how much better we would
understand the past, our past. But we
don't have the because of everything
being destroyed.
Bhaskar Bandit says, "Did you watch
Durander?" I haven't seen it yet. I
haven't seen it yet. I need to.
I definitely need to. Maybe in the next
couple of days I'll find some time and
go
grab a watch. So, what's my thought? As
you watch Bollywood rarely, I watch
Bollywood rarely. I'm going to break my
my my decision to not watch Bollywood
anymore just for this one movie, Blue
Durander.
Um the level of meltdown happening in
certain lobbies is entertaining.
Ecosystem has never taken a hit of this
magnitude before.
Yeah, the the meltdown that's happening
is in indeed very entertaining.
>> [laughter]
>> It is very entertaining. I mean, um you
open you open X, you're going to see
that. Yeah, meltdown happening. All
these uh
uh critics
establishment critics,
uh they are deeply unhappy with the
movie
and uh they are panning it or they're
trying to pan it without being too
obvious and it's not working.
And the same and and they're they're
complaining it's too violent. It's too
jingoistic.
And the same people have been um
lauding other movies that are way more
violent.
And they've been lauding all these fake
secular spy movies in which ISI and RAW
agents work hand in hand and have
romances. The same the same critics have
been doing that, but now they are
panning this movie. It's such a joke.
Those people
are so irrelevant today. Nobody cares
because this movie is doing so well. And
from whatever I've heard, it's a
tremendously good movie, a genuinely
good movie
as
not just Bollywood standards, but maybe
global standards.
So, that's what I hear about it and I
definitely need to go watch it. I was
Yeah, I think next day or two.
The ecosystem has never hit taken a hit
of this magnitude before. Indeed,
indeed, because see
the kind of
>> [snorts]
>> content that Bollywood produces is crap.
It's trash.
It's absolute trash.
And they keep on
peddling this mediocrity
week after week, month after month.
And their critics keep on doing their
job. But then suddenly, there's this guy
uh
Yeah, you know, this new movie has come
up which is not from within their
ecosystem, okay?
And it's so good.
It's better than way better than any
Bollywood movie that's come out in
recent times.
And the people are it's it's vibrating
it's vibing with people. People are
watching it. People are watching it
repeatedly.
So, I I know people who watch it like
two, three times. It's that good,
apparently.
So, the ecosystem is crumbling now. Now
people Now Indians for the first time
are seeing world-class cinema the way a
spy thriller actually should be.
Right?
And that's why the ecosystem has taken a
massive hit. And now now that Indians
have watched this sort of movie,
they will expect something of that
standard now because now the standards
have increased.
Now So, the expectations will also
increase. Now whenever Yash Raj kind of
trash movie comes out where Shah Rukh
Khan is dancing around trees with some
ISI agent woman and he's a RAW agent,
nobody will watch that movie now.
Right?
So, great. I'm so pleased. So, I need to
watch this at the earliest. I can't wait
to watch it.
Bhaskar Bandit again says, "Why Benazir
and Ziaul Haq were taken care of by
their alleged masters?" Oh,
did they get powerful internally or
change camps? We know the deep state
does all of this, but these two people
we have not discussed much.
Pakistan Pakistan, I am not I don't
really discuss Pakistan. See, yesterday
I did another show yesterday, Ask
Abhijit, right?
And some people were asking me, "What do
you think about this person? What do you
think about that person?" And my answer
was that I don't discuss random people
like some news reader.
Okay? I don't discuss news readers and
and
some what YouTube content creators who
who, you know, read out of um
teleprompters. I don't discuss them.
I will discuss world leaders. I'll I'll
discuss
Vladimir Putin, Xi Jinping, Narendra
Modi, Donald Trump. I'll discuss Elon
Musk. I'll discuss people of that
stature.
So, my the same principle applies here.
Who is Ziaul? Who was Ziaul Haq? Who was
Benazir? What were they?
They were simply puppets, sock puppets.
The real power was something else. They
were simply sock puppets. Somebody was
puppeteering them.
So, that's why I don't really discuss
these people because they were not that
important. But since you since you've
asked, since these are now historical
figures, so let me discuss them.
Ziaul Haq.
Well,
he got on a plane. He got on a on an
aircraft with the US ambassador whose
name was Arnold Raphel Raffle, I think.
Rafeal Raphael, whatever the hell the
pronunciation is. And there was a there
was some crates of mangoes on the plane.
And one of those crates exploded and the
plane blew up. And Ziaul Haq uh sadly
perished and so did the US ambassador.
Sadly perished.
So, that that's what happened to Ziaul
Haq. Uh late '80s, yeah.
Um And Benazir, well, she was shot by an
assassin.
Um she was at the time not the prime
minister, but she was campaigning or
something.
So, now
clearly, these were both assassinations.
So,
if it's an assassination, someone
assassinated them. Why would they have
been assassinated? Assuming it's a deep
state behind this.
Why would these people be assassinated?
Well, you assassinate if you are the
deep state, you assassinate somebody if
they become inconvenient. Or [snorts]
how can somebody become inconvenient?
Maybe they become too powerful and and
kind of start acting on their own agenda
rather than your agenda.
They start becoming independent instead
of being aligned with you.
In that case, you you eliminate such
such assets, such trouble-making,
problematic assets.
And overall, this this this principle is
that don't allow someone to be in power
too long. The longer somebody is in
power, if they are good, then they will
they will establish their networks. They
will
put down deep roots and they will create
genuine power structures that are
independent of you.
In which case, they can become a
nuisance. They can they can become
problematic. So, don't allow someone to
stay in power too long. Keep a rotate
you know, employ a revolving door
policy. What kind of policy do the do
the Americans employ in Japan? There's a
revolving door prime ministership. Every
few months, a new prime minister comes
and goes, comes and goes, comes and
goes. Same thing with the UK.
So, that way, there is no stability
politically.
Right? But that doesn't So, Japan and
the UK are technically democracies. So,
that that's what they do they do with
democracies. When you have a
dictatorship like we had in Pakistan,
you have to give the dictator slightly
longer time. Maybe not just 6 months or
1 year, maybe 5, 6 years. So, Ziaul Haq,
I think was then power for close to a
decade, which becomes too long. So,
that's why you take care of him.
Um and then you do a different
experiment in Pakistan. Then have a
different power structure come up, which
was essentially soon you had Benazir.
And then maybe Benazir had become
problematic. You know, that sort of
thing.
So, overall, see Ziaul Haq was simply a
sock puppet, uh a puppet of the US.
He was powerful because the US needed
him. And the US gave him that power.
They made him powerful. And the same for
Benazir Bhutto for a while. As long as
she was relevant, he is considered to be
the founder of the Taliban. Well, that
today the Taliban have absolutely no
love for her. I could assure you of
that. I'm sure of that.
So, there you have it.
Bhaskar Bandit again.
The US funded and embedded terrorism in
Bharat terrorism in Bharat using
temporary nation Pakistan and in 2020
put their own puppets in place.
Then why destabilize the state
who acts
as an asset
by allegedly giving arms to Balochistan
Liberation Army, Tehrik-i-Taliban
Pakistan, etc.
Well,
see the US funded and financed Pakistani
terrorism against Bharat from the 19
1980s onwards.
You know, 1979 is when things changed
when the USSR invaded Afghanistan and
then in 1980s onwards the Americans
poured in tremendous amounts of funds
and funneled weapons through various
means indirect means into Pakistan, sent
um
military, you know, trainer people who
would train the Pakistani military in
various terroristic and other
activities, etc.
And that's where that's how the
terrorism started in Punjab.
And then later you it spilled over into
Kashmir by design.
So, the US has done that. Yeah.
Now, nothing changed in 2020.
From 2012 to the 2022, Pakistan was a
Chinese asset, a Chinese vassal. Because
the Americans had kind of
uh temporarily given, you know,
cut Pakistan adrift.
But 2022 onwards, the US took control of
Pakistan all over again
after the ouster of Imran Khan. Now,
obviously the BLA exists, the
Tehrik-i-Taliban Pakistan exists. The
question is who is funding them? Do we
know that the US is funding them? I'm
not very sure about that.
Yeah.
So, if if the temporary nation is your
asset,
why would you want to destabilize it?
Well, that's a good question. Why would
you want to destabilize it? You can keep
some
instability going on just to keep the
keep your assets under control.
You know, if the country is running
completely smoothly, then they then your
assets they don't
the generals who work for you, they may
become too smug and they may become a
little complacent and they may feel
overconfident. But you keep the nation
unstable,
then it is a daily reminder to your
vassals, to your puppets,
that you know, you need to
you need to stay on your toes and don't
take anything for granted, don't take
your masters for granted, that sort of
thing. Uh but I'm not sure who's funding
the BLA, who's funding the
Tehrik-i-Taliban Pakistan.
Uh is the US doing it?
Can't say.
Is somebody else doing it? Is China
doing it? Why would the Chinese
fund the BLA? The Chinese won't fund the
BLA. TTP, I'm not sure about that. Uh
the Chinese are very careful about these
things, especially with, you know, with
issues in Xinjiang itself.
Who else could fund? Well, that's an
open question.
So,
one reason you could do this is to keep
your assets or, you know,
ensure that they don't become
overconfident.
Bhaskar Bandit says the Taliban denied
the Bagram airbase to the US. Yet they
receive 50 to 100 million dollars
allegedly per week in cash allegedly as
a weekly stipend. Not a vassal of the
US, but is but this is sort of
protection money or de facto
stabilization payments. What What is it
is the question. The question is why is
the US allegedly funding the Taliban?
See,
the US handed the country of Afghanistan
to the Taliban on a platter.
The Taliban did not win the war. The
Taliban did not defeat and eject the US
from Afghanistan.
There were
a There was a series of negotiations
that happened in Qatar between the
United States and the Taliban. And that
went on for a period of months, maybe
years. We don't quite know. It was much
of it was done in secret. So, maybe the
negotiations were were going on for a
couple of years, perhaps.
Eventually there was an agreement
between the US and the Taliban in Doha.
And certain aspects of that agreement,
the deal that was signed, certain
aspects of the deal are secret.
There are secret clauses to the
agreement.
And those
have never been revealed to the public.
And
as a consequence of this agreement, the
Americans simply withdrew from
Afghanistan and handed over the nation
to the Taliban.
And there was essentially no resistance
to the Taliban from the government, from
the so-called Afghan government, which
was nothing but a US stock puppet.
So,
it looks like a as a consequence of
those secret clauses in the agreement
between the two between the US and the
Taliban,
looks like as a consequence of that, the
Americans have some kind of secret
understanding with the Taliban
that you guys you Taliban will
play a certain role in Afghanistan which
will be beneficial to the US. In
exchange, the US will give a certain
amount of payment to the Taliban per
week, every week, whatever the amount is
to to so that the Taliban can continue
to run the country and
in a in a reasonably successful manner.
Now, what role could the Taliban play
that is beneficial to the US? Well,
in case you're not aware, the Chinese
are interested in Afghanistan. The
Chinese wanted to use Afghanistan
territory to build uh infrastructure for
the Belt and Road Initiative and that's
never happened. The Chinese were very
interested in copper deposits in the Mes
Aynak region in Afghanistan. That's
never happened.
The the the Taliban are keeping China
out of Afghanistan.
And there must be something else also.
You know, so that's that's the kind of
uh
service maybe the Taliban is providing
to the US,
a geopolitical service in exchange for
the money.
But obviously the agreement is such that
the Taliban remains sovereign,
Afghanistan remains sovereign. It is
dependent on the money that comes in
from the US, but it's not a tremendous
amount of money.
A hundred million let's say it's a
hundred million per week, that's 400
million dollars a month.
10 months is 4 billion.
So, it's it's about 5 billion dollars a
year, which is peanuts for the US, but
it's significant for the Taliban.
Um many nations can actually fill that
gap.
So, it's not like the US is
indispensable for the Taliban and so on.
But yeah, that's the kind of situation
that we have in Afghanistan.
Ritik Pawar says the US is 10 times more
powerful than India. So, we don't make
any moves against the United States. But
Pakistan, knowing that India is 10 times
more powerful than Pakistan, still makes
moves against us. Why is that?
If you look one layer below the surface,
you will see Pakistan
is backed up by the US.
Do you understand that Pakistan is
backed by the US?
And if if if Pakistan is backed by the
US, then it's like India against the US,
right?
That's why Pakistan makes moves against
us because they know they have the
backing of the big power.
And also they have the the confidence
that comes from apparently, allegedly,
not allegedly, being a nuclear weapon
state. So, they think that, you know, we
have that that red line that nobody can
cross, even India can't cross.
And
if if things go badly for Pakistan in
case of a war with India, at the end of
the day we still have the nuclear
option. So, these are the reasons why
Pakistan makes moves against us.
And the Pakistani military its a raison
d'être is
enmity with India.
The Pakistani military has legitimacy in
the eyes of the Pakistani Awam, the
people of Pakistan, only if India is
positioned as an enemy.
If there is long-lasting peace between
India and Pakistan, then the people will
start asking questions about the
Pakistani military. Why do you people
exist? India is not a threat.
So, why why is the Pakistani military
ruling Pakistan?
Why is your top general the dictator of
Pakistan? Why do you eat up so much of
our nation's budget? Why are the roads
so poor? Why is why why are all these
problems Why do the all these problems
exist in Pakistan? Why are you people
not solving our problems?
But if India is positioned as a big
threat all the time, then people will
ignore all the problems and worry about
India.
So, that's why the Pakistanis keep
making all kinds of moves against India,
you know, cross-border terrorism,
infiltration of
attempts to infiltrate terrorists into
India,
uh you know, whatever happened in
Pahalgam, all those things. They keep on
doing it from time to time. But of
course,
in the past 10-11 years, things have
been very different. Things have been
significantly different because every
time Pakistan has tried something, India
has hit back harder each time.
Right?
So, first you had the surgical strikes.
Then you had um
which was what, 2016 or whatever,
2016-2017.
Uh then you had Balakot, which was air
strikes in Pakistan. The third time you
had Operation Sindhu, which was a full
almost a full-scale war without you it
was an air war essentially for 3 days.
So, that's why it's getting harder and
harder for for Pakistan to do these
things, but they still keep on doing it
because they're backed up by the US.
Okay, Bhaskar Bandit says most beautiful
serene places you've visited in Bharat.
Look, most I haven't traveled that much
in Bharat actually. I would love to if I
get the time to visit every part of
Bharat, but I haven't
I've done that very much.
One of the nicest
parts of Bharat, you know,
we have great beaches.
I don't know, the last beach I visited
was the beach at Somnath.
That's not quite a tourist destination.
It's not very very well maintained. I'm
sure it can be done better. Uh the
nicest place I've seen visited is
probably Ladakh.
You know,
very beautiful. Love the climate. Love
the temperature. Love the altitude. Most
people can't take the altitude. I love
it.
Even Manipur is beautiful, but today you
can't really,
you know, we've we've messed it up.
So, I haven't traveled that much in
Bharat. The nicest place I've been to
because I like the cold, it's Ladakh.
Um yeah, that's what I can tell you.
Bhaskar Bandod again says, "Dyau
Dyau shpitru, Zeus Peter."
Not Peter Peter. Jupiter. What is a
Django?
What is a Django? Jago.
Oh, Django. It's D J A N G O. So, that's
yeah, you I think you watched
yesterday's live stream. Django Django
Reinhardt, the guitarist, yeah. Jago.
Khorasans Swarakshetra.
Please do tell us more examples and also
if possible it would be great to have a
separate visual video about this on the
channel. Okay. So, these are actually
very different examples. Dyau shpitru is
the
oldest of the Vedic gods that we know of
or maybe it's a he's a pre-Vedic god.
Dyau shpitru is
considered the father of Indra. Indra is
the greatest and most powerful of the
gods in the Vedic pantheon.
But his father is Dyau shpitru.
And Dyau shpitru was incorporated in
every
uh western and you know,
pantheon of gods
as the sky father.
So, Dyau shpitru became
Zeus Peter.
Clearly, Zeus Peter is derived The name
Zeus Peter is derived from Dyau shpitru.
But Zeus Peter, the Greek god,
has the attributes of Indra. So, they've
kind of combined the father and son
divinities into one, but given it the
name of the father in Greece. So, Dyau
shpitru becomes Zeus Peter in Greece,
but Zeus Peter is a have is a thunder
god.
Indra is a thunder god. Zeus Zeus Peter
also, I don't know if he See,
in Sanskrit I mean in in when it comes
to Indra, his primary weapon or his
weapon is Vajra. But Vajra has two
meanings.
Vajra means the thunderbolt. It also
means a hammer, a mace, a gada kind of
instrument
made from human ribs. But in later
European versions, it becomes a hammer
like the hammer that Thor has. Thor is
nothing but the Nordic version
of Indra.
He has two weapons. One is the
thunderbolt, the other is the hammer.
But the If you combine the two, it's it
is Vajra.
So, yeah. So, from Dyau shpitru and
Indra, we had Zeus Peter. Zeus Peter
became Jupiter.
Jupiter also doesn't have the same
attributes. He also kills a great sea
monster. And then you have Thor.
Uh Django Reinhardt,
his name was Jago actually. You know, as
a kid I suppose they parents called him
Jago because he would to sleep a lot or
something.
Uh Khorasan, well, it was Swarasthan.
Swarasthan.
Swara means sun. Also, it means gold.
So, Swarasthan
became Khorasan.
And Swarasthan was the region that is
the was Gandhar plus plus. Gandhar and
parts of
the western regions beyond Gandhar all
together. All of that was then later
called Khorasan.
Um
More examples. More examples.
Uh what more examples can I think of?
Not sure. I'll have to think about
something. I'm sure there are lots of
other examples like this.
>> [snorts]
>> Um
yeah, okay. Okay, I'll give you one more
example.
In in
in in Persia,
there is this
there is this very pretty common
Iranian or Persian name,
which is Khurshid.
Khurshid Khurshed. Look, let's go here.
Okay.
Khurshid or Khurshed, okay? So, it's a
Persian name, which means sun or radiant
sun.
Okay?
It's not an Islamic name. It's a Persian
name.
What's the origin of Khurshid?
Okay. So,
we know Lord Yama, right? Yama.
Yamaraj.
The god who
who's the final person you meet in your
lifetime, right? And it's the god who
takes you over to the to the afterlife
once you are done with this life, right?
Yamaraj.
So,
according to well,
mythology, let's say.
Lord Yama was the was the son
of Lord Surya.
He's the son of the sun.
So, that's why Yam was very bright and
shining apparently.
So, his father was Surya Dev.
Lord Surya, the sun, the sun himself.
So, one of the words for the sun in
Sanskrit is Swar, which also means
golden.
So, Swara means the sun. It also means
And
one of the epithets for Lord Surya was
Swarakshetra. Uh Swarakhetra.
Swarakhetra.
Swara means sun. Khetra means shining or
radiant.
So, he was called Swarakshetra.
Well, later the Persians could not say
"Sa".
So, they called it called him
Horakshetra,
which became Horshed, which became
Khurshed, which became Khurshid.
So, Khurshid or Khurshed means the sun
or shining sun, which comes from
Swarakshetra. There are so many examples
like these, you know. So, maybe I can
make a separate video about that.
Parthiban says, "I love geopolitics. I
want to work in a PE hedge fund AMC, but
I'm stuck in useless SYB com. Having a
career in India is painful. What should
I do?"
Well,
what you can do is leave the country
and go and work in one of these funds
that you like or one of these
um
in whatever field you like, in a hedge
fund, AMC, etc.
Uh how to leave India? How to do all
that? Well, you have to find a way.
I cannot tell you how to do it because I
don't know your circumstances and your
situation.
But where there is a will, there is a
way. You know, there is something called
agency.
A person who is low agency is a person
who only
who is not able to achieve what they
want in life.
They can't find a way.
They get stuck.
A person who is high agency is a person
who will find a way no matter what
happens. Just find a way. Make it happen
some Don't take no for an answer.
You knock on this door, you get a no.
You don't take no for an answer. Go
somewhere else. Knock on another door or
ask to to speak to somebody else. Find a
way to achieve what you want to achieve.
Find a way
to get
where you want to get.
So, that's one thing you can do. Maybe
go abroad and then work in a in a firm
that that resonates with you.
Um
but you do have to get a degree for
that, right? You are in SYB com. You
know that the
syllabus, everything is trash. It's
useless. It's just a waste of time for
young people. But at the end of the day,
you do get a degree, I suppose.
Otherwise Or or what you could do, you
could start your own business.
Um
but you have to find a way to do that.
Uh you love geopolitics. Maybe
geopolitics is your is your passion. But
you know, it's it's not going to make
you money.
Geopolitics is not a business, right?
Geopolitics is the understanding of the
world. Maybe you can If you have a deep
understanding of geopolitics, maybe you
can become a consultant, a geopolitical
consultant. Maybe you can,
you know, be a consultant consultant for
businesses which are risk exposed
because of geopolitical events. So,
there's so much you can do if you are
creative, if you have the right amount
of skills, if you have
if you have
the skills, the insights at a deep
enough level, you can do that. Or if you
want to work in a hedge fund, etc., then
you get your degree and get the hell
wherever you need to be. That's what you
do. At the end of the day, you remember
that your passion will not make you
money. Your skills will make you money.
And your skills may not be exactly where
your passion is. They may not be
aligned.
See,
your passion is something you can do in
your spare time. Maybe you love playing
the guitar.
But love playing the guitar, there's a
gazillion guitarists out there.
Only a small handful, maybe 0.01% will
make big money.
The rest of you guitarists, they they
barely survive day-to-day basis.
So, if you are a great If you have a
great passion for the guitar, well, play
a couple of hours every week. Maybe play
a half an hour every day.
Just do it for your for for your
relaxation or whatever. But
when it comes to making money, you have
to make money. You have to have a
career, livelihood. Well, you have to
develop skills which are aligned with
what the world needs. Maybe the world
doesn't need more guitarists. I don't
know, right? I'm I'm just saying. I love
the the guitar. I haven't played in in a
long time. I have a bunch of guitars
hanging on the wall.
They're gathering dust unfortunately. I
would I would love to play them every
day.
But I don't have the time right now.
It's one of my passions. I love it.
I used to be pretty good at that. I
don't know how good I am right now. I'm
sure I play a couple of hours every day
for a couple of months, I'll be back at
the same level, maybe higher. But I
don't have the time. See, it's one of my
passions. I have a lot of passions.
But you can't indulge in every passion.
You have to follow certain
certain avenues, and there's only a few
things you can do in life.
All right, sir. All the best.
Geopolitical to be Thank you very much.
Um
Where is it? Geopolitical to be Thank
you very much. Thank you very much.
Appreciate it, sir. Always good to see
you.
Uh,
Tanmay Deshpande says, "How will you
counter people who say idol worship does
not exist in Hinduism cause a very
specific religion who hates idol worship
is trying to prove it does not exist by
misquoting our scriptures."
I don't want to counter anybody.
It's not my business to so to go
fighting with everybody.
Right?
There are plenty of people whose a whole
livelihood is about countering and
fighting and all. I am not
going to do that.
Idol worship does not exist in Hinduism.
Well, look around.
Look around.
Does it not exist?
I mean, you have to be either blind or
mentally
impaired to say that idol worship, Murti
Puja, doesn't exist in Hinduism. Come
on. So, anyway, I'm not getting into
this this fight. It's not my fight. I
can't fight every fight, all right? I
can only do a few things in life. I will
stick to those things.
So,
I would The only thing I would say is
are you are you you are either
completely blind or you are mentally
impaired
if you think that Murti Puja doesn't
exist in Hinduism. Yeah? That's all I'll
say.
Okay. VSVS says Namaste. Well, Namaste
ji. Namaste.
WBR says, "Some in India believe that
large amount of trade
Some in India believe that the large
amount of trade between India and China
acts as a deterrent to prevent war
between the two nations. Is there Is
this a delusion?" Look.
Okay, let's Google this. What's the
uh,
annual trade between India and China?
Annual trade between
India
and China.
Uh,
in
billion USD.
So,
uh, 2024-25
127.7
billion.
Okay. So, what's the trade deficit like?
See, the Chinese enjoy a huge trade
trade surplus.
Okay. So,
in 2024-25,
it's roughly a hundred billion dollars.
So, if there is a trade
of 127 billion between the two
countries, China
if you
China essentially has a surplus of a
hundred billion dollars.
So, India is essentially funding China
in a way.
India is importing finished product
products and goods from China like
electronics, machinery, plastic,
pharmaceuticals.
And India is mainly exporting raw
materials.
So, this So, this is a failure of
India's manufacturing ambitions. We are
not manufacturing. We are exporting raw
materials.
African countries export raw materials.
And China is exporting
finished products and goods to India.
So,
is this
127 128 billion dollars of trade between
the two countries, is it
Is it a deterrent? Does it Does it Does
it serve as a deterrent
which prevents war between India and
China? I don't think so.
I'll tell you why.
So, there is something in India that
China wants. China wants Indian
territory.
More than that, China is worried about
India. India is the only nation in
Eurasia that can stand up to China.
And if India gets stronger and stronger
slowly slowly every year for the next 20
years, India will be able to genuinely
stand up to China, even pose a potential
threat to China.
And China doesn't want India to reach
there.
So, how do you prevent India from
reaching there?
Well, what is it that is
ensuring that India keeps growing? It is
India's government, the Narendra Modi
government, that has changed things for
India. And that's why India is becoming
more and more confident every year. And
India is genuinely growing. You can see
You can see the graphs.
So, the way to prevent India from
becoming a threat to China is to effect
a regime change in India. Now, it's not
easy to do that.
Now, but you can do it using India's own
system, which is democracy. Democracy is
a weak flawed system. And Indian
democracy is especially weak. India is
always one election away from disaster.
Okay?
So, how do you derail India's growth
trajectory? You do it by effecting a
regime change in India in India, which
is essentially by ensuring that the the
current government loses the next
election. How do you do it? By making
people By making people lose confidence
in this government. How can you do it?
By defeating India in a short sharp war.
Right?
And China claims Indian territory,
Arunachal Pradesh and whatnot.
And it would be easier for China to go
to war with with India rather than go to
war with war with Taiwan. Because if
India and China go to war, if China goes
to war with India, nobody's going to
come and stand for India.
But if China goes to war over Taiwan,
the US will fight China. Japan will
fight China. Even South Korea will be
present in the war by the Americans.
So, it makes more sense for China to
fight India.
So, in the future,
I think it is more likely that China
will initiate a war with India
before it initiates a war over Taiwan.
So, this is what China is doing right
now.
It doesn't like India. It It wants to
ideally break up India. It wants to
effect a regime change in India.
India has something that China wants,
which is Arunachal Pradesh and another
territory.
So, China is saying right now, "May
We'll wait right now. Maybe this is not
the right time to for war. Maybe in a
year, maybe in a couple of years. In the
meanwhile,
let's have India fund our military
growth.
So, let us have a
massive trade surplus with India. Every
year we earn a hundred billion dollars
from India and we dump it into our
military expenditure. So, India is
funding our military growth. That's what
this trade surplus that in China has
over India, that's the function it
serves. So, this big trade between India
and China, this large amount of trade,
it doesn't serve as a deterrent. It
serves as something that funds China's
military build-up
north of the India-Tibet border.
China is using India's money
to
to build up its military strength and
power north of the undemarcated
India-Tibet border. That's what's
happening.
So, this trade surplus, it does not act
as a deterrent. It acts as something
that strengthens China.
Okay?
Okay.
WBR says, "Oh, I I see that you have
changed your name."
>> [laughter]
>> You no longer have that Russian name.
Okay. Your opinion on free nations of
post-Russia forum.
Free nations of post-Russia forum. Which
forum is this?
A forum?
I'm not quite sure what you're asking
here, sir.
Free nations.
Were they unfree nations? Are you
talking about the nations that came out
of the USSR? I'm not sure what you're
asking, sir. I'm so sorry.
But, uh, if you could
formulate the question better, I'm I'm
sorry. I'm not sure what you're asking.
Sorry.
VSVS says, "Question by Rohan Sehgal
from AskAbhijit311. What's your take on
the third
interstellar object 3I Atlas?"
The,
you know,
there have been gazillion YouTube videos
about 3I Atlas.
And every two or three days they are
saying that, you know what, 3I Atlas is
an interstellar object that has come
from outer space, which which is not,
uh, natural in origin. It's an
artificial object. Maybe it is a
interstellar spacecraft. Maybe there are
aliens in there. Maybe it is showing uh,
signs of, uh,
of of of of
Maybe it is showing signs of, uh,
acceleration that is not natural. As in
maybe it's accelerating or decelerating.
Maybe Maybe
it is showing signs of propulsion. Maybe
it is showing signs of, uh,
you know, it being an alien object and
so on.
Well, you see, and and they've been
claiming
people have been claiming that, uh,
NASA, etc., are are hiding what's
happening.
They are They are not giving us the
correct data.
Well, my point is, look, from where I am
sitting, I don't have a massive
telescope that I operate.
I don't
have my own data. I can only rely data
on
on data that is publicly available. The
data that's publicly available from the
NASA and other space agencies doesn't
show
anything out of the ordinary when it
comes to 3I Atlas.
Okay. Uh, people have been saying that
3I Atlas is going to go around the sun
and then return to Earth. Well, is that
happen Has that happened?
So, now that 3I Atlas is simply going
It's It's gone around the sun. It's It's
going its own way now. It will be on its
way out of the solar system. Now, all
this frenzy the YouTube views frenzy is
dying down now slowly.
So, my point is, in the absence of any
data that
that shows anything extraordinary, I
would just say it's another interstellar
object.
And now that we have so many telescopes
out there, we're going to find more of
these.
So, that's all I can say.
As a scientist, you have to be
skeptical, super skeptical. Don't ever
rush to weird conclusions. I think even
Avi Loeb was saying that this is a
This is an,
you know,
an artificial object.
Well, I haven't seen any signs of that.
Yeah. Whatever evidence we have, it
doesn't show any signs of that. So,
that's all I can say.
Nano Mountain says, "How do you handle
setbacks and failures? How to be
optimistic about future goals
even if it looks
impossible now. Any tips on handling
negativity?"
How do you handle setbacks and failures?
Uh,
you have to be delusional.
You have to have delusional self-belief.
No matter what happens, I'm going to
keep going and I'm going to achieve it.
Now, first of all, it's like this, look.
If you have a goal that makes no sense
and you keep working towards it, you're
going to go in the wrong direction in
life.
So, first of all, you need to have a
goal that makes sense.
And what kind of goal are we talking
what what size of goal are we talking
about? You need to have a goal that's
that's achievable only in 10 20 years.
Assuming you're a young person, if you
are 55 when you have a 30-year goal, I
mean
be a little reasonable. Let's say you're
25 or 30 or something, then you can then
you should have a goal that is very hard
to achieve in 10 20 years.
Let's say you need to have a goal, give
yourself a 10-year target.
And that target should be almost
impossible to achieve in 10 years, but
not completely impossible.
Um
It should be such that there is nothing
in the laws of physics
that prevents it from from being
achieved.
And then you work as hard as possible
towards in that direction. And you just
don't work towards a 10-year goal. You
need to break it down into a
five-year goal, a three-year goal, a
one-year goal.
And then quarterly targets, that sort of
thing. That's what I do.
And then
when you're going towards the quarterly
target, sometimes you may miss a
quarter, you may make you may have a
failure.
So, in that case, you keep going. You
work
more. You work harder or you work
smarter.
And you should always have plan B, plan
C.
In case one goal doesn't work out, maybe
then you create a new goal. The point is
you need to first of all give yourself
the highest chance of success
>> [snorts]
>> by cutting out all the clutter,
cutting out cut out all the stuff by
cutting out all the stuff that wastes
your time,
by cutting out all the distractions.
So, give yourself the best chance of
success, be healthy, be strong, have the
right habits, um ensure that your energy
is high.
What's what's the best way of ensuring
your energy remains high? The right kind
of diet. And
staying away from the wrong kinds of
things like alcohol, tobacco, all that
stuff, you know.
And whatever else you may So, that's
what you do.
But even then, you may encounter
setbacks and failures because see,
there are two issues with goals.
One is there's a number of parameters
that's beyond your control.
Let's say you your your objective is,
let's say,
that I want to
There's a lot of people who go for UPSC,
right? So, I want to clear the UPSC exam
and and get a
and get into the government service.
Now, is that entirely in your hands? You
may study the hardest,
but at the end of the day, somebody else
will examine your papers and take your
interviews and all. And those people may
have their own biases.
So, for it is possible that no for no
fault of your own, somebody else for
somebody else's fault, you may not get
through.
So, then what do you do? So, then you
need to have plan B. You don't waste 7 8
years doing UPSC, right? You give it
maybe one or two attempts, then you move
on to something else.
So, that's what you do. Always be
positive, always have this delusional
self-belief, even
it it has to be you have to take it to
delusional level that no matter what
happens, I believe in myself.
Right? I may have failed in this, I may
have failed in that.
And always be be honest with yourself.
Don't don't blame it on others.
So, that's what you do.
And
it's it's often difficult.
Yeah? And what I can tell you is no
successful person has had
has had straight sailing.
The the more successful a person is,
the more times they have failed.
A person who is super successful is has
failed so many times you can't believe
it, you can't imagine.
And if you show me a person who has
never failed, I can I'll show you a
person who has never achieved anything.
So, the more you achieve, the
the more you're going to have have
failed. It's like that. So, you need to
have this
you need to have this high threshold for
pain if you want to be an achiever.
Yeah? You have to be able to take
setbacks.
And
move on nevertheless. So, that's what
you do.
WBR [snorts] says,
is the greatest asset of the US is
geography. Well, it's one of its great
assets, right? It's protected on two
sides by oceans,
the Atlantic Ocean and the Pacific
Ocean. And that's one asset, the other
asset is its gigantic geography,
right? It's gigantic it's it's a it's a
continent-sized empire.
The other thing is that they have
ensured that all other nations in the
Western Hemisphere are under their
control, right? Especially in the
Americas.
There's only one or two little nations
that the Americans still haven't
completely controlled. One is Cuba to
some extent, another is Venezuela.
Everybody else is completely aligned
with the US and they will never do a
thing that goes against US interests.
So, they have worked on this really
really really really hard the past
couple of centuries,
right?
So,
it's not just the geography, it's also
the fact that
they they have worked very hard on it.
But yeah, maybe the greatest asset
overall is the geography. If you take
just a snapshot of the US today, take a
look at the map, then yeah, the way
things are today,
it's incredible. But they have worked
very hard to make it happen the way it
is right now. Because initially, the US
was just a small reasonably small nation
compared to what it is today on the East
Coast of the continent. And then they
went westwards,
expanded westwards relentlessly until
they reached the Pacific.
So, they worked really hard to do that.
Obviously, they had to genocide
everybody in the who stood in their way
and and the natives
reduce them. They they they they have
been fighting the natives for almost 500
years,
exterminating the natives
for roughly 500 years.
Yeah?
Right, okay.
James James says, "No Hindu who has
received English education ever remains
sincerely attached to his to his
religion. It is my firm belief that if
our plans of education are followed up,
we will have zero idle believers." Lord
Macaulay. Lord Macaulay was a visionary
and an incredibly successful person who
whose vision was indeed carried out, was
executed by
the British overlords, but the British
occupiers of India.
And
and his vision is still being executed
today, Lord Macaulay's vision.
You know,
in India, if you want to succeed in
anything, you have to speak good
English.
You have it is indispensable to have an
English language education.
If you want to have a job in a good
company and a the high position. If you
want to want to have a good job
anywhere, you need to be able to speak
good English. You need to be able to
give your interview in English. You need
to be able to write very well in English
and so on. So,
India has been more and more
Macaulay-ized, colonized, deracinated,
etc. generation each each succeeding
generation.
And the government of India today is
still
hell-bent on on making Lord Macaulay's
dream come completely true.
That's what the government of India is
doing right now through its educational
policies.
So, yes, Macaulay came up with this
incredibly
powerful plan to totally enslave India
mentally.
And it's worked. India is super mentally
colonized today.
So, thank you for bringing drawing our
attention
to this
important important fact, um James. And
today, a lot of Indians it's it's quite
fashionable to to to
to
you know, abuse Lord Macaulay.
I would say you should learn from Lord
Macaulay.
See, Macaulay was not serving India, he
was serving his people.
And if you think what he did was evil,
well, so be it.
It is what it is, see.
In in geopolitics, there's no good or
bad, there's no right or wrong.
Geopolitics is amoral.
The objective in geopolitics is to
achieve
whatever is best for your nation.
Now, the UK was an imperial system. It
was an empire, the British Empire.
And what was good for the for what was
good for for England, for the for the
British Empire? The
complete domination over India
is what they sought to achieve. That was
beneficial for the US for the UK.
And that's why Macaulay came up with
this plan.
And the plan was implemented.
The point is
now that Macaulay is dead, now that
India is technically free from the
British,
why is the government of India still
implementing, executing, and still using
the Macaulayan system? That's my
question.
Macaulay did whatever was good for for
his for his country.
But it's bad for our country. The
question is why is our government not
dismantling the Macaulayan structure?
That's the that's the big question.
That's the big question. And that's very
very very concerning, very problematic,
and
one wonders what's going on.
Yeah? So, anyway, James, thank you for
raising this point, very important
point.
Okay, VSVS James is Konglu Mia from
Superpower Bangladesh. I don't think
James is a Konglu Mia.
I don't think so.
I think James is on our side. And I
really appreciate James.
He always raises these really important
points.
You may not like that the way he raises
these points,
but I appreciate what he's doing. Thank
you, sir, James.
UMX Glo Haha says, "Ronaldo looks a
brown. Why is called the right white
person?"
I don't call him a white person. You
mean Cristiano Ronaldo? He's brown.
Cristiano Ronaldo is not white.
A lot of Spanish people are not white,
really, okay?
Um Cristiano
Ronaldo.
I mean, how can you call this gentleman
white?
He's not white.
He's a brown person.
I would say the same applies to Rafael
Nadal, okay?
Rafa
Nadal.
I mean, look at this this guy Rafael
Nadal. He's not white.
This is not a white person. He has the
same same skin color as me essentially.
And the the same applies to Cristiano
Ronaldo.
>> [snorts]
>> So a lot of people is Cristiano Ronaldo
Romani? Is he Is he Romani?
>> [snorts]
>> Is he Romani? He's He's Portuguese we
know that.
But he's not typically identified as
Romani. Uh Ricardo Quaresma we know is
Romani. And Quaresma has the same skin
color as Ronaldo.
The thing is this. I I spoke about the
Romani people yesterday after a while.
So
there's a lot of people of Romani
ancestry
in Europe.
A lot of people have Romani ancestry.
But they are very really afraid to
disclose the fact that they have Romani
ancestry because then they will be
subject to
horrible discrimination.
There's a lot of people in in especially
in in Iberia which is Spain and
Portugal.
Okay?
So
there's a lot of people
like that. So it's possible maybe
Cristiano Ronaldo may have Romani
ancestry but maybe he's never disclosed
that.
Yeah, maybe Rafael Rafael Nadal also
possibly who knows. We don't know. I'm
I'm saying in any way
the people of Spain, Portugal and Italy
they are much darker skin than the
people of let's say Norway, Sweden,
Denmark.
Right?
I would not consider the people of
Spain, Italy even Greece to be
white in the sense
the same sense as the Nordic people. I
would not consider them to be white.
The Romans
Well the Romans did not consider white
people their equals. You know that?
They considered white people inferior.
The Romans.
Anyhow so that's the deal. So
Ronaldo does look brown because he is
brown. He is not a white person in my
opinion.
And that's okay. What's the big deal?
Why do you have to be white?
Just because you're European doesn't
mean you have to be white.
Okay.
Uh Nimish says Nimish Bhardwaj says
thank you for the live chat sir. Well
thank you so much. Thank you so much for
your viewership. Thank you so much for
your encouragement.
I appreciate it very much.
Uh Sagar Gare says World War I book
recommendations please. Well I have done
so many book recommendations. I need to
put out some videos some some
um
some videos uh video clips. I need to
make some video clips about that. Now
when it comes to World War I one
um I would say there's a book called The
War That Ended Peace.
The war that ended peace uh by Margaret
MacMillan is it?
The war that
ended peace book by Margaret MacMillan.
And this book is about
well essentially
how the First World War happened.
The road
to 1914.
So what happened in the months that
preceded this war?
Yeah.
Uh so that's a great
That's this is a great book. Yeah? And
you will see I'm sure good reviews of it
on on Amazon.
Um
The Guns of August is another great
book. Yes. Barbara Tuchman.
The Guns of August is another fantastic
book.
So and and I'll tell you what these are
great books but they're pretty hard to
read. You need to
expend a lot of mental energy to read
these books. But yeah these two books I
would say The Guns of August and The War
That Ended Peace. These two
start with these two books.
>> [snorts]
>> Rajat says Pranam GenZ leader.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay. Did you again a chance to look at
the CMB dipole and its alignment with
the Earth's equinoxes? Look we don't
have the answer. I I did take a look at
that.
We don't know why it is so. Okay so let
me explain what is the CMB dipole and
what is
the question of its alignment with
Earth's equinoxes.
The CMB dipole what is the CMB? It's the
cosmic microwave background. What on
Earth does cosmic microwave background
mean?
To put it very simply
if you go out into outer space empty
space
you will find
the remnants of the first light in the
universe.
Those photons are still flying around.
The afterglow of the Big Bang itself.
So
for about 380,000 years after the
universe was born in the Big Bang the
universe was too dense to and it was
opaque to light. It was opaque to
photons. And then eventually it it
became transparent to light and and
light started
flowing everywhere. So that first light
those photons still exist in the
universe. You can still find them in in
in space.
And that's called the cosmic microwave
background. It's got a temperature of
about 2.7 or something Kelvin.
Okay? Almost close to absolute zero.
Very cold very faint light.
Now
the Earth
the solar system is moving in a certain
direction in the galaxy. Right?
The sun is moving around the center of
the galaxy like every other star. So
because of that because of the movement
in the CMB rest frame
we the the Earth is moving through
space. So it's So in on on one side
there is
you're going to see
um
the energy
you will see difference in temperature
of the cosmic microwave background
radiation because of the Doppler effect.
So uh
on one side you will see colder colder
CMB on the other side you will see
slightly warmer CMB. So that's called
the CM
the dipole.
Okay what's it look like? This is what
it looks like.
Okay you can see uh
a difference in in in temperature.
Where we are coming from where we are
going. So when we are
where we are coming from on the back
it's going to be slightly cooler
slightly colder the energy will be
slightly lower.
And over here
where we are going it's going to be
slightly warmer.
That's the deal.
And I'm sure AI will explain to us the
largest temperature variation
temperature or energy variation the
energy of the
of the cosmic microwave background
photons.
Because the local group of galaxies is
moving about 600 km per second relative
to the CMB's rest frame etc. So that's
the CMB dipole. Okay?
Now the CMB's dipole
that
the difference in the temperature it's
incredibly shockingly well aligned
with Earth's equinoxes.
Okay?
So see the Earth
goes around the sun.
And if you take the
the Earth goes around the sun in an
elliptical path in an elliptical orbit.
And that ellipse
traces a plane. Okay the plane of the
solar system.
And the Earth
it rotates at an angle to that.
Okay? To the ecliptic. So the So the
plane of the solar system the plane
that that is traced out by the Earth's
revolution around the sun that's called
the ecliptic.
And
the Earth is is is its rotation is is at
about 23 degrees to the ecliptic.
So
the plane that's traced by Earth's
revolution around the sun it aligns
almost perfectly with the CMB dipole.
And it is believed that that cannot be
entirely random.
There's got to be some reason for that.
But we're not quite sure what the reason
is.
And that's the thing. So it's a big it's
a big mystery.
That's the deal. So it's a really
interesting
paradox it's a really interesting puzzle
cosmic puzzle that we have.
And we don't quite have an answer to why
this
phenomenon
exists.
And that's
one of the big open mysteries in physics
today. So yeah that's the deal.
Shishir Upadhyay says how will India
society progress in the next 30 years?
Well ask me to look into the future. I
don't know.
How will Look it depends on so many
things so many factors.
Assuming that India keeps on grow
India's economy keeps on growing the way
it's growing. See right now it's about
8% growth.
Assuming it's even 6%.
If India keeps growing at 8% per year
then in 20 years it's going to be a
middle income nation.
It's not going to be a low income
nation.
So India's GDP per capita will be like
12 15,000 dollars in today's dollar
terms.
Right now it's what? 3 4,000 I don't
know what is India's GDP per capita
today.
India GDP per capita India
G
GDP per capita
in USD
2025.
What What do we have? It's about 3,000.
Yeah?
But if it keeps growing at about 8% per
year
what will India's GDP per capita
Okay let's not ask Google. I'm just
saying if if it continues for 20 years
at 8% we're going to be a middle income
nation. If it continues at 6% per year
even then we'll be close to a middle
income nation. So if that happens
India society will be more prosperous
than what it is today.
Um
that's what I can tell you. But if there
is some problem if there's a war and if
things don't go the way they go then
there could be issues in society. So it
depends on a variety of other factors. I
cannot see the future.
I can only tell you that if things go as
they are going right now, India will be
a middle income nation in in 20 years,
not even 30 years. In 30 years, if it
still keeps growing at 8% per year,
we're going to be a reasonably high
middle income nation.
And that's
what I hope happens.
But it's going to be very inconvenient
for some other nations, and they will do
their best to prevent that from
happening.
Which means that nations like the US and
China will try and disrupt India's
progress. Of course, they will, because
it's beneficial to them. It's in their
interest to to disrupt India's progress.
How could they disrupt India's progress?
One thing is they could
affect regime change or attempt regime
change operations in India. They could
tamper with India's electoral system,
which has happened in the past. Even in
2020,
which year was it? 2024?
You know, there most likely was inter-
external interference in India's
electoral system electoral process. So,
they could attempt a regime change
operation. They could interfere in
India's electoral process.
They could induce India to go to for
some nation to attack India militarily.
A lot of things could happen. So, I have
no idea which direction India's society
will go in in the next 30 years. It's
impossible to predict the future.
I think there's a high likelihood of war
between India and Pakistan in the next 1
or 2 years, maybe next 5 years
definitely.
The longer India waits for a war with
Pakistan, the stronger Pakistan will get
because the US is is bolstering
Pakistan, bulking up Pakistan. So, I
think there's a high likelihood of war
between India and Pakistan in the next 1
or 2 years.
There's also highly likely higher
likelihood of war between India and
China than China and Taiwan.
So, we could face serious
challenges in the next 5 years.
But if we somehow avoid
a military conflict and we somehow avoid
a regime change and we somehow do
everything right and avoid all all all
issues, then in 20 years we'll be a
middle income nation. So, lots of ifs
and buts here. So, I can't really
predict what's going to happen.
Critical thinker says, "How to develop
advanced problem-solving skill in
physics?"
How do you become a better
Let's say you want to be a boxer.
How do you become a better boxer?
Do you become a better boxer by reading
books about boxing? No, right?
You become a better boxer by practicing
boxing. Yeah? You do a certain set of
drills and exercises every day. You warm
up. You wake up at 4:00 a.m. You warm up
for 5 minutes, then you go for a
5-km run, maybe 8-km run. You come back,
you have a meal, then you go and do
whatever exercises you do you want to
do, you know,
your push-ups and your squats and your
jumps and all that. Then you go and have
another meal, then you go and box. You
go and do some, you know, punching bag
work. You can you do some speed work,
light light bag, then you do some the
heavy bag work. Then you take another
rest. Then you go and do some sparring.
So, that's how you become a better
boxer, and you have to do this over and
over and over and over again. It's very
boring.
You have to do it for months on end. You
have to do it for a couple of years on
end. Then you start becoming a boxer.
You go and do some actual bouts.
Then you have to progress through the
through the ranks, and that's what you
do. So, that's how you become a better
boxer. Now, how do you become
better at solving problems in physics?
Not by reading how to solve problems, by
actually attempting solve to solve
problems. You understand the theory as
quickly as possible. Don't waste a half
of the time reading theory.
Understand the fundamentals from the
theory. Understand the core equations.
And then grab a book full of problems
and start solving the problems.
If you fail, if you don't figure it out
how to if you're not able to solve a
problem, go back to the fundamentals.
Understand the fundamentals again.
Understand how the equation was derived,
what what the equation means, and how to
use the equation and the maths. So,
which means that you have to be good at
math.
You have to be See, it's
Problem-solving in physics is
essentially solving math problems. But
the math means something physical.
So, you do understand the correlation
between the the the math and the actual
physics also. So, that's what you do.
You solve a gazillion problems. You
spend as much time as possible solving
problems, not reading theory.
That's what you do. And you start with
the very basics, with the very
fundamentals. You start with the very
basic math.
You don't start with advanced problems.
You start with the simplest problems.
You You master that, then you go one
level up, then you master that.
How do you master? Not by reading, but
by solving problems. Solve as many
problems as possible. So, that's what
you do. All right?
All the best.
King Ritwik says, "I worked in various
states, Tamil Nadu, [snorts] Karnataka,
Odisha, Maharashtra, Kerala. The best
people were from Odisha, very
well-behaved and treat outsiders very
well. We should We should accept Odisha
as the best people."
Okay, well, that's your experience, and
I'm glad that you found Odisha very
good.
Uh
I haven't worked in so many states, so I
can't say
I I cannot I
So, my experience isn't as as as broad
as yours.
But I have In my experience, the people
of Odisha are wonderful people. No
question about that.
So,
um
and I I have a special connection with
Odisha because I was born in Odisha.
So, and
I've only been in Odisha 3 months of my
life. Okay, so I I I don't really know.
The last time I was in Odisha was when I
was 3 months old.
After that, I've never returned,
unfortunately. I would love to.
So, I'm I'm glad that uh
you like Odisha that much. Though, I'm
sure the people are wonderful, and
Odisha has a great history also, a very
glorious history.
Uh So, yeah, thank you for sharing your
experience, and thank you to the people
of Odisha for for being some of the best
people we have in the country.
UMX Glo Haha says, "Iran
Glo Hal Glo Haha UMX
Glo Haha." All right, whatever it is.
Iran in India posted
Iran in India on X post that Shatrang
Shatrang Shatranj, yes,
was taught to them by an Indian and they
mastered it and became better than
Indians, and they introduced the game to
Indians that we couldn't even understand
the game.
Okay.
I kind of saw that post briefly. It was
about some some there was some video in
it.
The The see, look, there's no question
about the fact that
chess came from India. Everyone knows
that. Chess was invented by Indians
during the Saraswati Sindhu phase of our
history.
Uh
And obviously, if the Persians played
chess, they would have learned it from
Indians. No question about that.
Now, I'm not sure if the Persians
mastered it and became better than than
Indians about that. I'm not sure if that
is what the post was about.
And
when they introduced a game, which game
to Indians?
When they introduced a game to Indians,
we couldn't even understand the game.
Which game are you talking about? Some
other game?
Are you saying that the Persians
introduced some other game into India?
I don't think that's what the post was
about. The post was only about chess.
And I did not watch the entire video
because I don't have the time to watch
long videos, even if they're 2 minutes
long.
But uh
Yeah, okay.
All right.
Okay, WBR says, "An
Indian vlogger went to Russia to meet a
World War II veteran who told how
German soldiers would used to put
Russian babies under tank tracks. Why is
this not talked about? Instead, all the
focus is on atrocities in Berlin by
Soviets."
>> [snorts]
>> Look, war is pure horror.
War
is horrible. If you're a soldier, your
job is to kill.
Right?
And once you start killing killing
killing killing, you will see everyone
as the enemy who are on the other side.
I'm not I'm not trying to justify
anything, by the way. I'm just saying
that for many people, eventually the
boundaries will blur.
They should not blur.
As a soldier, as a person, you have to
be disciplined. You have to be
professional. But
as we know,
all wars
eventually lead to atrocities. I mean,
look at what the Americans did in Iraq,
Abu Ghraib, and whatnot. Look at what
the
the Canadians as UN peacekeepers did in
Somalia.
I mean, wars always lead to atrocities.
The longer a war lasts, the more
atrocities there are. Yeah?
In the modern era.
Uh
And And we know that the Russians
suffered a lot at the hands of the Nazi
invaders. No question about that. Yeah?
So, my point is our coverage of history
has to be balanced.
It cannot The problem is that, you know,
like Napoleon said, "History is a bunch
of lies written by the
is a is a set of lies agreed upon." And
the objective of writing history is to
distort what happened and to serve
political and other agendas.
Sometimes the the the purpose is to
justify an invasion. Sometimes the
purpose is to justify the occupation and
brutalization of a country. That's what
the Europeans have done with India.
They've sought to justify their their
occupation of India for 2 and 1/2
centuries, the British, by claiming that
Indians had a horrible culture and that
and they had to be civilized.
Right? Caste and Sati and whatnot.
They've invented all these things, all
these stories.
And they actually imposed the caste
system upon India, the four four fold
caste system, which we still continue
today.
So,
the right way to do history is to just
put all the facts out there.
Uh but history has become a tool
of propaganda, and that's why we have
these issues.
So,
why is this not talked about? Because
one side won, and another side lost.
And that's why the winning side
The Which was the side that won? It's
not about who won the Second World War.
The Soviets defeated the the Germans in
the Second World War, right?
And yet,
the the Nazi atrocities against the
Russians are not that spoken about, even
though the Soviets won. Because
afterwards, the Soviets lost the Cold
War. And that's why the Western
narrative is the predominant narrative
today, even though the Soviets did win
the Second World War.
So, that's why
today we have a certain set of
narratives out there. And ideally, it
shouldn't be like that, but we live in
the real world.
Biju Saikia says, you can check it on
Google. Since 2021, China's GDP is stuck
at about 18 trillion. What happened to
the growth? Okay, let's find out. Let's
first of all check this.
China
China GDP
uh graph.
billions of USD. Okay, so that is done
for in rupees. Okay.
Show us the graph, bro. What is this?
Statista. Let us see Statista.
Do we have Statista?
Um economy of China China GDP macro
trends. Let's take a look at macro
trends. Do they have a graph?
Okay, 3 years, 17.88. Ooh la la, what
has happened here?
Looks like you are totally right. Since
2021, it's stuck at 17 or 18 something.
Let's go back. Let's check this from
somewhere else.
Um comparing United States and China by
economy. Okay, let's do that. Sure.
Let us see. Do they have Do you have a
graph?
Uh a decline. Go away. Shoo.
So, China
China is stuck at 18 3 years. What
happened?
Uh 2020 2019 is the pandemic year. Then
was a pandemic.
21 22 23. I don't know what happened. I
think the pandemic did the
Was it because of the pandemic? Was it
because of something else? I have not
really looked into this. Did the
pandemic
cause a tremendous amount of damage to
the Chinese economy? Did the Chinese
economy get stuck because of because of
it? Is there some other causative
factor?
Not sure. I will have to actually look
into this. Right now, I don't have the
answer to what happened to the growth.
Why is China stuck at 18 past 3 or so
years? Something seems to have happened.
Uh it's it's not like the TFR has caused
the GDP to suddenly get stuck. The TFR
The Chinese TFR has has has collapsed a
long time ago.
Could be has to be something else. I
have to look into it. I don't have the
answer right now.
Uh Rajat has become a new member. Thank
you so much, Rajat. Let us all welcome
Rajat to the membership of this channel.
Thank you very much, sir.
Uh UMX glo ha ha ha ha says, Jihadist
terror attack in Australian beach. My
thoughts.
Horrible, terrible, tragic.
Unacceptable.
Pakistanis, right?
I'm pretty sure at least one of the
persons is a Pakistani. This happened
today, Bondi Beach, I think. It was some
kind of a some kind of Jewish event or
something.
And a couple At least a couple of
Pakistani terrorists
At least a couple of gunmen were there.
Should we call them gunmen, or should we
just call them terrorists? If there's an
attack on in India, Western
news outlets will say that gunmen have
attacked Indians. They won't say
terrorists have attacked Indians.
They'll say gunmen.
Let us Let us see how the Australian
media has reported the the Pahalgam
attack.
SMH. Sydney Morning Morning Herald. Look
at this. Sydney Morning Herald. Gunmen
killed dozens of tourists at Indian
resort in Kashmir.
So, this is how Australian newspapers
and media
report terror attacks in India. Gunmen
killed dozens of tourists. Gunmen.
Gunmen.
Yeah?
Worst attack. Not terror attack, but
worst attack.
Have they used the word terror anywhere?
Okay, they say that
police has described this as a terror
attack, but they refuse to describe it
as a terror attack.
So, this is the attitude of the
Australian media.
W- What are the
I mean, Australian media.
Austra-
Militants. Okay, it's militants now.
Yeah?
SBS
Does it say it gunmen? BBC will say
gunmen.
Um okay. So, look, I am
Ob- Firstly, what's happened in in
Australia today is tragic. It is
horrible.
It's unacceptable.
It seems to have emanated out of
Pakistan. Pakistan is a terrorist
nation.
I looks like there have been uh
I don't know how many casualties. Some
people seem to have lost their lives,
which is horrible.
What can I say?
What can I say? Terrible.
I also want to point out to the
Australian media likes to portray
terrorist attacks on Indians as attacks
done by militants or gunmen, not by
terrorists.
It's an
Maybe not the right time, wrong time.
There's no right or wrong time.
So, why does the Australian media like
to portray terrorism against Indians as
not terrorism? Why is that?
And it's also interesting
that you know, the United States has
decided to ban immigration from certain
countries.
Countries of extreme concern.
And this list of countries from which
immigration has been banned, this list
does not include Pakistan. Pakistan is
not a country of concern apparently for
the for the Americans for for for Donald
Trump and his regime.
And see what happened in Australia.
So, the West seems to have a death wish.
They seem to be in deeply in love
with Pakistan
and the kind of ideology and the culture
that emanates out of Pakistan.
Well, all right. You pay the price for
that, then.
What can I say? Very unfortunate,
tragic, horrible, unacceptable.
Biju Saikia says, will we ever find a
theory of everything? Probably not.
Probably not. Why do I say probably not?
Because we are not
The universe is most likely too
complicated for
us to understand. Us as a species. See,
our species has a limit
to its intelligence.
The most intelligent human beings, what
is their IQ going to be like? One See,
if you are
What's the genius level IQ? It's 150,
right?
If you are 150 and above in IQ, you are
a genius. So, I think the highest IQ a
human can have is potentially around 180
or 200. Which is like super genius.
But maybe you need an IQ of 500 to
understand
the universe properly and actually find
a theory of everything. It's possible.
Yeah?
So, there are limitations to our
intelligence, and that's why it's likely
that the universe is so vast and so
complex that maybe we may never find a
theory of everything.
VSVS says, I went to Shanghai and
Beijing in 2023. The city centers were
beautiful, but literally a 30-minute
drive outside led to trash, poor people,
and potholes. Do you think they are just
better at PR? They are
unquestionably
a million times better than India at PR.
They have many of the same problems that
India
has.
It's not like India is the only nation
that is corrupt in
China is super corrupt.
But China executes people for
corruption.
And they also
you know, brush a lot of the corruption
under the carpet.
China has corruption. China has
pollution. China has potholes. China has
homeless people. China has slums. China
has all these problems.
But
this is all
kept away from the public view.
And what the Chinese do is they hire
They pay so-called influencers, etc., to
show the good parts of China.
The Chinese government is concerned
about China's image.
That is where China is different from
India.
The Indian government doesn't care about
India's image.
Otherwise, they would do something.
They They you See, to improve India's
image, you have to do two things at the
same time. One, improve the conditions
in India.
Improve the conditions.
Don't simply try to hide it.
Improve the conditions. So, that takes
hard work, but that's not happening.
At at various levels. In some levels, a
lot of work is happening.
See, the government of India, the
central government, has done a
tremendous amount of work since 2014.
Okay, no question.
But at lower levels, at state,
districts, other levels, I don't know
what's happening. And that's where the
image of India comes from, right? The
ground level.
And the central government doesn't have
I don't know that
Let's forget about the positive factors.
But so on the one hand, you have to
improve the conditions on the ground. On
the second on the other hand,
you have to go on a PR campaign to show
the good parts of India and possibly not
show the bad parts of India. The same
thing China is doing.
But we don't we don't do that. The
government of India, when I say it's not
concerned about India's image,
what I mean is that they don't
invest money for PR. They don't spend
money for PR exercises.
They don't invest in influencers, maybe
10,000 influencers from various
countries, maybe 1,000 influencers from
various countries.
You pay for the travels, you pay for the
gear, you pay them a certain monthly
retainer with the with the understanding
that every month they'll put out a
certain number of videos or reels or
whatever showing India in a good light.
It doesn't take a lot of money to do
that.
But India doesn't do that at all. India
is not concerned. That's what I mean
that by when I say India is not
concerned. The government of India is
not concerned. The government of India
doesn't care about India's image. If it
would, it would hire people. It would
pay people. It would commission people
to
to create these campaigns.
The Chinese do it. The Chinese pay lots
of influencers.
Good money
to show China in the best possible
light.
And that's why these these people, these
these YouTubers and Instagrammers and
all, they will relentlessly put out
reels and videos showing the best parts
of China and keeping the bad
[clears throat] parts out of the frame.
The Chinese are super
good at PR. India doesn't care about PR.
That's the problem. I just don't
understand why the government has why
the government of India has this strange
attitude.
WBR [snorts] says mechanical designs
engineering or quantum your interests
your my interest.
My interest is the whole world knows is
is quantum mechanics.
I am sure mechanical designs and
mechanical engineering is interesting.
Aeronautical
engineering is interesting.
Everything is interesting. But if I had
to pick a pick one, it would be quantum
mechanics, of course. And that's what
I've picked in the past.
Okay, Al Genib says chances for life as
we know
to move on or begin
chances for life as we know to move to
or begin independently on the moons of
Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, Neptune is
Neptune is sun gradually becomes a red
giant pushing Goldilocks zone further
out
plus plus life sustaining parameters
holding well.
Look,
when will the sun become a red giant?
Maybe in 4 billion years.
How old is the solar system? 4.
What? 4.54 billion years?
So the amount of time the solar system
has existed, it's going to have to exist
for another that much amount of time
for the sun to start becoming a red
giant.
Around that much time.
Yeah? And as the sun slowly expands and
becomes a red giant, the Goldilocks zone
will move outwards, no question about
it. So eventually at the at the peak of
the of of the red giant phase, the
our
earth is going to be swallowed up by the
sun.
So the so the Goldilocks zone will go
outwards, further and further outwards.
Uh how will the what will the solar
system look like at that point in time?
We are not quite sure.
The solar system has been evolving over
time.
There have been some planets that may
have been ejected out of the solar
system deep in deep antiquity.
Um the orbits of the planets have recon-
have been reconfigured reconfigured over
time. It's possible that uh Venus may be
the orbit of Venus may go somewhere else
in the future. You know? These are not
entirely 100% stable orbits. They will
change over over hundreds of millions of
years, maybe billions of years.
Uh that's one thing. Secondly, um
what are the chances for life to to
begin in- independently or move on to
the moons?
Chances, well,
to begin independent there could already
be life
on maybe Europa, maybe Encel- Enceladus,
maybe on Titan.
A different kind of life than what we
can you know, what we can potentially
imagine. On Titan, it will be totally
different kind of life because the
chemistry is totally different there.
It's it's methane based chemistry in in
on Titan. When it comes to Europa and
Enceladus, it's a subsurface oceans that
we have there. Even Pluto may have a
subsurface ocean.
So as the Goldilocks zone goes outwards,
maybe Europa becomes an ocean world.
Maybe Enceladus also becomes an ocean
world and the the several kilometer
thick ice crust just melts.
Then you you could have life there that
could
be similar to the kind of life that we
have in the oceans of our planet. All
kinds of possibilities are open.
And the uh
the change in the sun and its its
transition to
becoming a red giant, it it will not
happen over a over a time period of
weeks. It's going to happen very very
very slowly and it will happen over
evolutionary geological time scales,
which will give
life the time to evolve in
and and and and adapt to the changing
situations, circumstances.
Okay, King Ritwik says, "When will India
reach that stature, power, confidence
and take back what's ours so that China
will fear us and call Tibet Arunachal
occupied Lhasa?"
>> [laughter]
>> When will that happen? Look,
once again,
India is currently growing the last last
quarter or whatever it was, India's
economy grew at 8%. Despite Trump's
tariffs, despite all the issues in
India's economy grew at 8%.
Assuming India's economy keeps growing
at 8%, in 20 years we will be a middle
income nation like what China is right
now.
Even if we grow at 6% per year, in 30
years we'll be a middle income nation.
Okay?
Uh
so
when and and China's economy is not
growing that well now.
China faces issues, but China has
advantages that we don't have. China is
not a democracy. China has a government
that's way more efficient than ours.
China already has a massive industrial
base. We don't have it.
China has a fantastic education system.
We have the world's most rotten
education system. So
we can have an economy that's comparable
to what China has today in 20 years,
let's say.
But if our system is still rotten,
then we will never get our act together.
So we're going to have to change all
those things. It it may
if we are to be optimistic, maybe in 20,
30 years we will have that stature,
power, confidence, all that. Yeah?
Uh we'll have to become an industrial
power.
We'll have to become a manufacturing
power
to be comparable to China. It's not just
the size of your economy.
You can have money,
but you if you don't know how to make
things, then what will you do with that
money?
Huh?
You may have the greatest culture and
your greatest economy, but if you can't
defend yourself because you don't have
the industrial base, what do you do?
But obviously we are going we are taking
steps in the direction. We will now soon
have hopefully indigenous jet engines.
We will I don't know about AI. I don't
know what we're doing with AI and so on.
But yeah, hopefully we go in that
direction. So maybe 20, 30 years if you
are to be optimistic. Yeah?
Rehman Baloch says, "Assala-
Assalamualaikum from Lyari, Lahore,
Pakistan." Well,
namaste back to you, sir. Greetings and
good to have you, Rehman Balochji. Good
to have you. Lyari Lyari is in Lahore.
All right. Good to see you, sir.
Thank you.
Um Sangam Kumar says, "Can China beat
the US in Taiwan as leaked report says?"
Um
The Chinese can take Taiwan if the
Americans are okay with it. Otherwise,
China will get nothing.
The Americans are just way too powerful.
If China tries to invade Taiwan, they
will not only have to fight America,
they will also have to fight Japan
because the Americans control Japan. So
they will press Japan into action. Japan
has a frighteningly good navy.
Japan is very very good
uh you know, technologically.
The Americans can allow Japan to become
a nuclear power next weekend if they
want to. Japan has the technological
know-how to do that.
The Americans can even press South Korea
into action.
If China tries to take Taiwan and
America doesn't want China to take
Taiwan, the Chinese won't succeed no
matter what happens.
Right? So it's not that easy. It's very
hard.
Pratham
Maydekar says, "To what extent are
claims of Durandar true in Lyari?"
I still haven't watched it, so I can't
say.
Hopefully this week this coming week I
will watch it. Then next weekend I can
answer this question. Right now I don't
have the answer. Sorry because I haven't
seen it. Right? Sorry about that.
Polarized says, "Houses have nully
nullies nullies higher than the road,
then dust and water stagnates.
If nullies are leveled properly,
much of the dust would be in sewer and
not on road."
What's a nully? Nully?
Nully means what?
Nully? Nully means uh
canal?
Nully?
Nully is a
gutter. What is it?
Okay, houses have
canals or gutters higher than the road
then dust and water stagnates if these
canals or or gutters are level properly,
much of the dust would be in the sewer
or not on road.
Okay, you are talking about dust dust in
India.
The dust why is there so much dust in
India?
I'll tell you okay, let's let's discuss
the issue of dust. There's no question
that India's cities, towns, villages
etc. are very dusty.
Let's go to the map to understand what
what on earth is happening. Yeah, let's
look.
So, here's India.
Okay, the the subcontinent. Very dusty
place.
You go and and let's see let's go to the
heart of India and just place a marker
there. What's the latitude? Latitude is
23° north.
Longitude is 79. So, if we go to the to
a similar latitude maybe in Vietnam,
okay?
So, here also it's 20 21 23 23 Okay.
So, if you go to Hanoi, which is at a
similar latitude, you don't have that
much dust. You go to let's say if
perhaps uh
this place in China, Fujian province,
26° of latitude. You don't have that
much dust. You go to for example
um
if you go
See, Mexico has a is at a very similar
latitude
latitude set of latitudes as India.
Here you have today this is very similar
to Indian latitude. That's why
you know, the climate of Mexico Mexico
is so similar to India. But in Mexico
you don't have that much dust
compared to India. Mexico is dusty but
not as much as India. The question is
why is India so dusty and all
and and what can we do about this?
The major reason why India is so dusty
is because we have a big desert in
India, the Thar desert. See, look here.
The Thar desert. Huge
big
arid barren region.
It has sand dunes. It has dust. And that
is the reason
why there is so much dust in the Indian
subcontinent. The Thar desert. Secondly,
deforestation.
Okay?
10,000 years ago, you had forests all
across India.
Today
about 10 or 15% of India is covered by
forests.
And uh that is another reason.
And third is construction etc. but the
major reason is the Thar desert.
The major reason why why you have this
issue in India
so much so much dust is because of the
Thar desert.
The Thar desert is what uh
uh makes India so dusty. And of course
we can
there must be
there are lots of things in the
government of India can do to
to make India less dusty, but some of a
significant portion of it comes from the
desert. It's a natural phenomenon. Okay.
Biju Saikia says, "Do you think there
should be term limits on our leaders?
Does India have the potential to be an
autar
autarky?
Autarky.
Do you think Do I think there should be
term leaders?
Well, term
term term limits term term limits.
Well
it has pros and cons. Yeah? Term limits
have their
advantages, their disadvantages. If you
have So, what term limits do is that it
they ensure that if you have a bad
leader who's not good enough but who's
somehow popular
then if you have a two-term limit, then
even if that person is popular
they can't do too much damage to the
country
because they only have two terms.
But on the other hand, if a leader is
fantastic for the country but can only
serve for two terms, then it's bad for
the country.
So, it it it works both ways. Now, you
have term limits in the United States.
In the US it doesn't really matter who's
the president because the president
doesn't really run the country. The
president simply draws attention
to himself. It's a himself. And the
president usually does whatever
the people who are really in power they
want him to do.
So, in the US it doesn't really matter.
And term limits okay, good. So, do I
think there should be term limits on our
leaders?
Term limits make sense if your system is
good.
What do I mean by a good system?
A good system is a system that will no
matter what happens give you good
leaders.
A good system is a system that
identifies
leadership talent, rewards leadership
talent, and elevates leadership talent.
That's the right system. That's the
right system.
The Indian system is not such that it
identifies and rewards
meritorious leadership talent.
The Indian system if you look at the
history of India the past 80 years
it hasn't given us the best leaders. We
are lucky that we have someone like Mr.
Modi right now.
Imagine the alternatives.
Yeah?
So, I think for term limits make sense
only if your system is guaranteed to
give you high quality
leadership alternatives to what is
currently there.
In that case, if there is one person who
is in power but five other equally good
or even better leaders who could come to
power, then term limits make sense.
But if you have a situation in in a
system where you have one good leader
who's in power right now but 78
not so good leaders who are waiting to
take over, then term limits will destroy
the country. So,
so given the current system of India, I
think term limits don't make sense. If
we change the system and give and you
know and and have a system that's
guaranteed to throw up good leaders,
then term limits make sense. Right now
in this system, term limit term limits
are very dangerous for India.
Udbhav Sharma says, "In a future war
with AI systems using AI systems, how
could counter AI technology of a country
defend against or neutralize enemy AI?"
Can't.
You can't have AI fight AI. You can have
systems fighting systems, not AI
systems, physical systems. AI is not a
physical thing.
Right?
It's not like you have a missile that's
flying and you have a missile that
destroy a missile. So, you shoot down a
missile with another missile like what
we have today, right? You know,
missile defense systems.
But AI is is not something you can shoot
down with another AI.
There is no no such thing as counter AI
technology.
See, understand how wars will happen in
the future. You will have drone swarms.
They what as one example
of an offensive weapon.
Drones can be used as offensive weapons.
We know that very well.
And the best way to use drones is in
swarms. Maybe a hundred drones dwarf
drones at the same time. Maybe a
thousand drones at the same time.
And how will the drones be controlled
and coordinated? Through AI.
And AI will not be on the drones.
The the drones will have
onboard chips, but they'll be
interconnected
through whatever systems and they may be
connected to satellites. And through the
satellites or whatever the systems, they
will get orders from the AI. And the AI
will know the AI will be system sitting
somewhere else far away.
The AI will know exactly which where
each drone is in relation to the others
and in in relation to the target
physically, geographically. And the AI
will ensure that the drones have the
best survival best chances of surviving
against
offensive
measures.
That's And this is the country And the
other country will also have its own AI
system, which will target which will use
the which will control the defensive
uh
military systems.
So, the country with the best AI wins.
But it's not like AI is fighting AI. AI
is controlling equipment. The both AI is
a controlling equipment. And the AIs
that have the that have access to the
better equipment and the AIs that are
more intelligent will prevail. That's
how it will work.
Pratham Medekar says, "You can go to the
midnight shows of Dil Aashiq Now." Uh is
the show Is the movie being shown at
midnight?
That'll be fantastic.
Yeah? I'm not sure if See, right now
it's almost 10:00 p.m. here where I am.
And
uh I'm
yeah,
completed nearly two hours of this live
stream.
And I still have uh
40 50 super chats left to go.
So, I don't think I'll be able to see
the midnight show tonight.
But that's fine. That's fine.
Um
Anantha Subramanian says, "Which key
lessons from history do most people
miss?"
I can make a two-hour video about that.
It's not something I can explain in uh
couple of minutes. There are so many
lessons from history. You can write a
book about the lessons from history. And
it's not like lessons historical lessons
are necessarily universal.
Each country
has a specific set of lessons it needs
to learn from history.
So, if you
are sitting in let's say Romania
the historical lessons you the key
historical lessons you
need to learn may be different from the
key historical lessons a person sitting
in India need to needs to learn.
It will be different from Mexico.
So, it it is context context dependent.
It's geography dependent. It's it's
depends on the context of the geography,
the culture, the specific history of the
country, place, etc.
Uh but overall what what key lessons do
we miss?
Let's
one key lesson
that we have to understand
is that the
system of governance that works the best
is not democracy, it is autocracy.
It is dictatorship. It is
Look at the history of the entire world
the past 2,000 3,000 years.
The system that has that has been the
most enduring is monarchy, which is what
dictatorship, right?
A democracy is is it is is a facade,
it's an illusion. It's a polite illusion
created to give people the the the sense
the false sense of confidence that they
they they have the fate of the world in
their hands. It's not true. It's always
it's it's a means to mislead people.
Democracy is an illusion.
That's one key lesson of history. The
second key lesson of history I would say
is that all major historical change
happens through warfare.
Okay?
All major historical change, every major
historical change has happened through
warfare, through violence.
Understand that.
So there's I'm sure there are
way more key lessons, but I can't go on
forever about that right now in this
live stream. Maybe I can make a separate
video about that.
VSVS has gifted 10 memberships to
people. So VSVS I
really really appreciate you. You did
that yesterday also. You gifted I don't
know how many memberships, a lot of
memberships and you're doing that today
also.
Thank you so much for
your kindness
and not not just to me and my channel,
but to the people who are viewers here.
Thank you so much. I really appreciate
that.
Godliness Godliness says Pakistan now
has Saudi bank US patronage and Chinese
help also Turkish technology.
Do you suspect a more violent and
dangerous Pakistan in the future?
I expect war between India and Pakistan
in the next one or two years.
I'll be very surprised if there is
there isn't a war between India and
Pakistan in the next one or two years.
The longer
India waits, the more powerful Pakistan
will become because of foreign help.
There is nothing
in Pakistan that makes it powerful.
But the Pakistanis
have
all this help coming in
from various nations. At the end of the
day it's all been coordinated by the
United States.
The United States is now
implementing a policy of containing
India.
And the best way to contain India is by
using rogue rogue nations, terrorist
nations like Pakistan.
You keep your hands dirty and help
Pakistan do the dirty terror work and
all that work for you. You fund them.
You give them F-16s. You give them arms,
ammunition, weapons, training.
You have your allies or your your
vassals give them money.
Right?
And the US and China both agree that
India needs to be contained. So even
though the US and China are adversaries,
they agree about India.
So the longer India waits and sits back
the more powerful Pakistan will become.
I expect a war between India and
Pakistan in the next one or two years.
Right.
Udbhav Sharma says Pak Pakistan to
release Mehra Layari movie to counter
Dorinda. All right. Let them do it.
Ankita Kashyap has also gifted
10 memberships. Ma'am, thank you so
much. You also did that yesterday, so I
also really appreciate you.
Thank you so much for being so kind to
this channel and to its viewers. Thank
you so much, ma'am. And VS VS has gifted
10 more memberships. Thank you once
again. Thank you so much.
Really really appreciate you, both of
you. Thank you.
Okay, My Rhythm says Breaking India by
Rajiv Malhotra is genuine. Can I read
it? Sir, you decide what you read or
not. I
Breaking India, Rajiv Malhotra.
I haven't read it.
But so so I I haven't read it, so I
can't say.
But uh
I have heard a lot of good things about
it.
And uh Mr. Malhotra has
a very
good reputation, no question about that,
right?
So I would say you should go and find
out for yourself whether it is good
enough and whether you like it or not.
Based on what I've heard, I'm sure you
will be you will you will gain something
from it. Yeah?
So yeah.
I would say if you are curious about it,
definitely go ahead and read it.
Godliness says we want Ram Rajya, but
the reality is corruption is thriving
with no police, judicial, or education
reform and now reservation in the
private universities of Maharashtra. Are
we fighting a lost war? I don't know.
I Look,
Ram Rajya is the ultimate objective. It
is the greatest
objective, right?
But before we reach Ram Rajya, we need
to slowly improve things.
We can only improve step by step by
step. Eventually
someday we will reach Ram Rajya, the
greatest
state a nation can have, society can
have.
Look, I think
everybody understands that there seems
to be a lot of corruption
in various parts of India, which is the
legacy of the past 80 years of
misgovernance.
Right?
And that seems to be the hardest nut to
crack.
Because it looks like allegedly the
entire system may possibly
hypothetically run on corruption.
Uh so
it's it's it's it's uh
I've I've been I've said this so many
times.
It is the biggest problem that faces
India.
And if India needs to get it wants to
get its act together, it has to launch a
war on corruption.
The other thing is the reforms at
various levels. Yeah,
various levels.
And the one of some of the most
critical, crucial, urgent reforms that
we need are education reforms.
Now I've been saying this for over like
four years now.
This channel has been active for about
four years. I've been saying that.
Uh maybe
Are we fighting a lost war? I don't know
about that. I don't think it's a lost
war. Uh maybe it will take longer. Maybe
there are problems and and issues and
obstacles that we sitting over here
can't see perhaps. Maybe the government
is better aware of how things are. Maybe
these things will take time.
I would say be optimistic. I'm an
optimistic person. So I'm I don't think
it's a lost war. We will win eventually.
UMX [snorts] Gluhaha says B.Com
absolutely horrible. Should I leave this
degree? I don't know, sir.
Do you have a plan B?
Okay, so you're doing a B.Com. It's
horrible. Whether you're doing a B.Com
or a B.Tech or whatever, it's going to
be horrible. The Indian education system
is garbage, it is trash. Your teachers
are trash, your textbooks are trash. The
syllabus is trash, the curriculum is
trash.
The exams are trash, everything is
trash. It's a waste of people's time,
but without the degree you will you will
not get a job. My point my question to
you is Yeah, I know, I agree, it's
horrible, but do you have a plan B? If
you quit
if you quit your education, if you
you know, if you walk out of college or
whatever, like Steve Jobs did,
Steve Jobs walked out of college. Yeah?
Elon Musk walked out of his PhD
PhD program.
My point is if you if you do that, do
you have a plan B? What will you do? If
you have a viable plan which is likely
to succeed, then go for it. Otherwise,
stick to your degree.
Biju Saikia says we Hindus consider
asuras evil and devas as good, but
ancient Iranians used to worship asuras
and consider devas evil. Why did they go
into this path? Not ancient Iranians,
more recent Iranians, Persians. Look,
before Zoroaster was born, India and
Persia had the same culture, same
religion. We worshipped the same gods,
same deities.
Zoroaster when he was born, when he was
a little baby, his parents were Hindus.
He was Hindu.
But then Zoroaster came up with this new
thing. He inverted some of the elements
of our religion. So
we consider asuras to be complex. We
don't necessarily consider asuras to be
evil. All asuras aren't evil. Asuras are
complex. And they have slightly more
negative qualities than the devas.
That's how we look at it.
But in Persia, what Zoroaster did was he
inverted this entire thing and he made
the the asuras or the ahuras, because
they can't the Persians could not say
sa, they said ha instead. So he said
that the ahuras are the good guys and
the devas are the bad guys.
Uh why did they go in that direction? I
don't know. But somehow Zoroaster seemed
to seems to have been a very charismatic
person and he got the entire population
of Persia, including
maybe not the entire population of
Persia, but he got the emperors
to take up his path and that's why
it became the official state religion of
Persia, more or less de facto state
religion of Persia.
How it happened, we don't know.
The records are lost. Why are the
records lost? Because Alexander came and
destroyed the Persian empire and and
burned the capital city of Parshpur.
Parshpur.
The Greeks called it Persepolis. The
actual name was Parshpur.
And the Greeks they the Macedonians they
burned it, they destroyed everything and
no records are left.
So we in India know that our ancient
universities and and libraries all
across the subcontinent were destroyed
and burned by the Turks. Where in Persia
that happened
century what more than a millennium
before. The Greeks destroyed Persia.
And that's why we don't know when
exactly Zoroaster lived and how he was
able to get his religion
and make his religion the de facto state
religion of Persia. We don't know how it
happened.
Narendra Reddy
Narendra Reddy says, "Can I do a
business with no job experience?" You
can.
But if you have job experience, um
it give you it makes you better equipped
to understand things.
But you don't need to have job
experience to do a business. You just
need to get the fundamentals right. You
need to be very careful with your money
and you need to scale and etc. You know,
it depends on the kind of business
you're doing. So, you don't necessarily
need job experience to do a business.
There are lots of business people who
have never worked a job, but they do
business. But you need
to learn how to do business.
See, there are various business
communities in India
where
you learn from your parents because it's
it's it's the family business, right?
So, typically if you are a young person
in such a household, you will be made to
work in the in the family shop.
Which is kind of like getting job
experience, but you also get business
experience. So, if you don't have any
job experience, it's it doesn't
necessarily mean that you can't do a
business, but you have to be careful.
You do acquire the right skills at the
earliest.
Rituparna says, "Lenin versus Stalin
versus Putin, who is the greatest? Why?"
Lenin, Stalin, see thus far Stalin is
the I'm not saying Stalin is good. He
killed lots of people. He his policies
led to the deaths of millions of his own
people.
But he is the man, Stalin,
who transformed this this destroyed
nation into a superpower.
So, thus far Stalin is the greatest.
Lenin
I would say Stalin is way greater than
Lenin Lenin.
Um
Of course, Stalin mismanaged some
things.
He put Crimea into the Ukrainian SSR
for administrative reasons be which
caused a lot of problems and
problems decades later as Putin knows.
Could Putin be greater than Stalin?
It's too early to tell.
If Putin gets his succession right, then
he will be remembered as Putin the
Great.
But if he gets his succession wrong,
then everything he has done will be for
nothing.
Okay?
So, Putin will need to be careful about
his succession. He is no longer a young
man, Mr. Vladimir Putin. He's in his mid
early or mid 70s.
Uh let's say he has 10 years more
before, you know, he will have to
relinquish power at some point in time.
So, he will have to ensure
the succession goes right and the right
person comes to power after him.
If the wrong person comes to power after
him, then everything Putin has worked
for
will be lost. So, the succession is what
matters. If he gets the succession
right, then he will be remembered
remembered in history as Putin the
Great. Otherwise, mhm.
Uh Biju Saikia says, "Do you use any
mental models?" I'm sure I do, but I
don't know what they're called. I have
my own mental models. I've not studied
textbooks that this is the mental model
called so and so and this is how you use
it. I use mental models, but I don't
know what they are called. I have my own
proprietary mental models, which I use
for various things. Um not sure what
they're called.
Amisha Mishra says, "Skin, hair care
tips and as a student care of eyes."
Skin, hair care tips. Well, it depends
from person to person. Everyone's
biology is different. Some people have
dry skin, some people have oily skin,
some people have certain kinds of hair,
some people have straight hair, some
people have curly hair. I have curly
hair. You may not see it from here
because I always keep it
nice and tidy, but my hair is pretty
curly.
Okay? That that's sort of hair.
So, everyone's kind of, you know,
parameters are different. What I would
say is that understand the kind of skin
that you have and
take care of it. If you have oily skin,
make sure it's dry. If it's dry skin,
make sure that you moisturize.
Keep it simple and have a routine.
Similarly for hair.
So, ideally you should wash your hair
like I don't know, three times a week.
Use don't use soap to wash your hair.
When I was a kid, I used to wash
I I used to use soap to wash my hair.
Use shampoo, use a conditioner. I mean,
use whatever is good. Ideally, it should
be
more as natural as possible, as chemical
free as possible.
Uh that's sort of thing. What about
eyes?
When it comes to eyes, don't read don't
When you're reading, don't keep the book
too close to your eyes.
Keep it at a good distance.
Um and you know, if you spend a lot of
time reading, it's very likely that you
will end up with glasses.
That unfortunately as a student, you
have to read. You have to read a lot.
And that's going to be a a thing.
So,
I would say spend some time every day
outdoors.
Look at
allow your eyes to look at large long
distances. Maybe look
spend some time looking at the sky look
looking at objects that are like several
kilometers away, hills, mountains,
whatever.
So, that your eyes
get used to different focal focal
lengths, not just the short focal
lengths, that sort of thing.
And yeah, that's what I can say. But as
a student, if you spend a lot of time
reading as every student does, it's
highly likely that you will get
uh you will have to wear glasses at some
point in time. Hope not.
Uh if you're a sports person, if you're
a cricketer like, you know,
I remember where I had read about Sunil
Gavaskar that he used to ensure he never
read fine print.
He would have somebody else read it for
him. He would never read fine print. He
made sure that he took as good care of
his eyes as possible, which means never
read
longer than you need to.
But as a student, you can't do that. So,
yeah, you will have to take as many
precautions as possible.
And uh what else? Yeah, get adequate
sunlight. Not too much sunlight.
And um
I suppose eat carrots for your eyes. I
don't know, vitamin D or something.
Vitamin A, whatever it is, yeah.
Okay. VSVS says, "If no 2014, then we
wouldn't demand anything." Yeah, if Mr.
Modi had not won in 2014, then I don't
know what's what shape India would be in
today. Then Indians would not be
confident and not not be as demanding as
they are today.
So, today Indians have aspirations.
Indians say that why is this country in
such bad shape?
India should be a first world nation by
now. Uh Indians want India to be a
superpower.
That's because of the change, the
transformation that's happened in India
since 2014. India was in terrible shape
in 2014.
In
young people, people who are what, 15,
16 years old have no idea what India was
like
20 years ago.
It was in terrible shape. India has come
a long way since 2014. And because India
has
grown and advanced so much, I know the
problems exist.
And that's why Indians are focusing on
those problems now that
India's economy is so much bigger now,
why do we still have those problems?
So, we would not demand these things if
we were if if we were still in the in
the position that we were in 2014, we
would not have those aspirations. We
would not have those dreams, those
hopes, those demands
that things need to change bet for the
better much faster now.
Right?
So, we were at zero. Now we have then we
reached one, then from one we have
reached 10. Now the question is now that
we are at 10, how do we reach to 100?
That's the question.
WBR says, "Free nations of post-Russia
forum
claims nations like Bashkortostan
Bashkors Bashkortostan,
Tatarstan, etc. are colonized by Russia
and should become independent. It great
it gained traction after 2022."
That way you can claim everything needs
to be independent. I would say go to
France and say that Brittany must be
should be independent.
Comoros should be independent. Go to
Spain. In Spain you have Catalonia. You
have a a
What is it called? What What is it
called? A mhm The Basque The Basque
region, the Basque country should be
independent. In every nation you can
start all these independent independence
movements.
What about the US?
The Lone Star State.
What about it?
What about Quebec on Canada?
So, you know, all these
these these ideas that they gained since
2022 because in 2022 the Russia did
something that the West did not like.
Russia started looking out for his for
its own interests. It drew a hard red
line when it comes to Ukraine.
And yeah, so
there was a deal.
So,
Bashkortostan,
Tatarstan, etc.
This is these are all
you know, it's all a matter of
convenience. When the West wants to
pull, you know, pressurize
you, they will start
start uh
making these narratives and all these
claims popular.
And they're doing similar things with
India also right now.
So, yeah, yeah, yeah, indeed.
James James says, "So, we gave you a
head start of several millennia,
and Clive of India still knocked over
your civilization in a few years."
Yeah, well,
Clive of India, yeah. Robert Clive, such
a
Okay. It's a live show, I should be
polite.
I should maintain some some politeness
and not use certain words for the
person.
The point is this. Look, India had a
head start of several millennia. No
question about that, yeah.
What happened?
Why did Clive get the opportunity to do
what he did?
Because
before the the Christians the before the
the Europeans came to India, India was
already in bad shape.
It It got into bad shape because it was
occupied by the Turks for several
centuries. Various parts of India, not
the entire subcontinent, various parts
of India
reaping
expansion of the occupation, the Turkic
occupation. How did the Turks
get into India?
Because they started invading India,
attempting to invade India when India
was fragmented. India was no longer
under one single empire. The The
previous empire was the Gupta empire
which had which occupied which which
encompassed the entire subcontinent.
But empires come in cycles, come and go
in cycles. So, the imperial cycle ended.
After an empire ends, there's a period
of maybe a couple of centuries or
multiple centuries of fragmentation.
The same thing you find in China and
every other imperial systems.
So, the Turks invaded India
when India was fragmented and that's why
they were able to over a period of like
three, four centuries make inroads into
India and eventually by the 1700s,
they
occupied a very large portion of the
subcontinent. Then the Marathas took
over.
And the Marathas had this great
opportunity to eject all foreigners from
India.
But there was infighting among the
Marathas, too, and the Maratha empire
collapsed rather sooner than it should
have. And that's why
Clive and his and his likes were able to
do what they did.
And they were pretty rapacious, evil,
despicable people, weren't they?
I mean, so were the Turks, no question.
And that's how it goes. So, my point is
there's what's the point of having a
great culture? What's the point of
having great civilization or a great
economy when you cannot deal with
barbarians? And that's the lesson of
history India needs to learn.
It's not enough to develop your economy.
We are growing at 8% per year. We will
be a middle-income nation in 20 years.
Good. But what about your military
power?
Your military strength should also
increase proportionately.
Right?
Maybe more than proportionately. If
you're growing at 8% per year, your
military expenditure maybe should grow
at 10% per year.
Because the larger your economy is, the
more valuable your country is.
And the more others will be tempted to
to
to do something about it.
So, yeah, that's These are the lessons
of history that we have to learn and I
appreciate James and thank you, James,
for pointing this out and having me
speak about this.
James.
Godliness says Pakistan, even after May
conflict, was ready to go all out
against India. That 3,000 kg explosive
in Faridabad was enough for mass
casualties. Their intention is clear,
war, and we still don't respond. Why?
So, the Pakistanis launched a missile at
Delhi.
And it was intercepted over
Sirsa in Haryana in Haryana, right? A
couple of hundred
pretty close to Delhi.
It was intercepted by one of our air
defense systems.
And you know, there are these CCTV
videos that you find that you will see
on social media. There's this big flash.
You can see the Indian air defense
missile being launched and there's a big
flash in the sky and later there's this
gigantic bang.
Huge bang, which means that the missile
the Pakistanis launched had already
re-entered the atmosphere.
Because otherwise, if it was intercepted
outside the atmosphere, there'd be no
audible bang.
So, the missile was intercepted within
the Earth's atmosphere over Sirsa in
Haryana.
So, that was a missile that was launched
at Delhi.
I'm not sure what it contained.
Did it contain Did it contain
conventional explosive or was it
something else?
So, the Pakistanis
Yeah, they they had decided to go after
Delhi.
And Pakistan, as long as it exists, is
going to be a threat to India.
So, the only solution to the Pakistan
problem is the
Balkanization of Pakistan.
That's what India has to achieve.
Now, why are we not responding as you
say?
Because Pakistan is not merely Pakistan.
When you fight Pakistan, you're not only
fighting Pakistan.
Pakistan is backed up by the most
powerful nation in the world.
And the nuclear weapons Pakistan has are
most likely American nuclear warheads.
So, that also is something we have to
factor in.
We are not fighting See, when Russia is
fighting Ukraine, who was Who is Russia
fighting?
Is it really fighting Ukraine?
Ukraine would The Ukraine war would have
ended in 2022 itself.
Why is it still going on?
Because all those arms, ammunition,
weapons, money, funds, everything that
Ukraine has, it's coming from the West.
What is the West? It's NATO nations. Who
controls NATO? The US.
Russia is actually fighting a US proxy
in Ukraine.
Similarly, if India and Pakistan fight,
India is fighting an American proxy once
again.
So, that's the deal.
And
if we initiate a war, the Americans will
impose sanctions on India.
So, we'll have to be very careful about
how to deal with Pakistan. But the next
time there is a fight, we have to break
Pakistan into pieces.
We have to end the threat once and for
all.
We can't keep living with this permanent
blackmail on our western frontier.
So, it has to
This This issue will need to be fixed at
the earliest. I expect war in the next
one or two years.
Fast snail. Love that. Fast snail says,
"Wouldn't Russia want to fix India-China
relations?" No.
First of all, Russia can't fix
India-China relations.
Secondly,
understand the dynamics.
Russia is currently
in the position of being a junior
partner of China.
Right? And Russia understands that
India-China relations
It's not some some some machine that you
can put a few screws and bolts on and
fix the problem, right?
It's not like that.
Understand what's central to the
India-China issue.
Why are relations bad between India and
China?
Relations are bad not because India has
been poking China and harassing China,
but because
China
first firstly
refuses to demarcate the India-Tibet
border.
And secondly, China claims more Indian
territory. That's why relations are bad,
not because of India, but because of
China.
China is more powerful.
India is less powerful. China is about
four times more powerful than India.
Now, what can Russia do to fix this?
Nothing.
What can Russia do?
Russia can do nothing to fix it.
China is right now economically more
powerful than China than Russia.
And Russia is significantly
significantly dependent on China for a
variety of things.
Um So, that's the situation.
Now, if India gets more power becomes
more powerful, it would be beneficial
for Russia.
Because then Russia will have
a more powerful ally in India.
So, it's it's complicated.
And even if And And
So, it's not about Russia wanting to fix
India-China relations.
It's not like we create a cozy company,
cozy cozy group. Each nation has its own
interests. For Russia, China is a
threat.
But right now, China is indispensable.
But long term, they know that China will
is going to turn on Russia. China is
going to turn on Russia in the next 5
years.
Okay, that's going to happen.
And Russia knows this.
So, if Russia is going to if China is
going to turn on Russia and start
threatening Russia and creating problems
for Russia in 5 years, why would Russia
want to fix India-China relations? Even
if it could.
Doesn't make sense.
Okay, Fast snail says,
"When and how did Russia become a
Christian nation?" Interesting question.
So, the Slavic people So, the Russian
people are Slavic people, right?
It's an ethnic ethnic group.
Who are the world's Slavic peoples?
The Russians, the ethnic Russians are
Slavs.
The Ukrainians are Slavs.
The Serbs are Slavs.
Okay, so that's how it is. So, the
Slavic people
historically were
followers of the old
Indo-European religion.
The old Indo-European religion
is this religion that was found all
across Europe in different
manifestations.
It is nothing nothing but a different
form of the Vedic religion. Okay?
That's what it was. Now,
now over time you had, you know,
for example, when you had the king the
European king Charlemagne
He lived in the first millennium the
last half of the first millennium AD.
What was it? 800 AD, 900 AD? Let's
quickly take a look at that. He did the
northern crusades, very brutal crusades.
Let's see.
Uh Charlemagne.
He was also called Carolus Magnus. He
was king of the Franks. Yeah, 774
king of the Franks, 778, died 814 AD.
So, the second half of the first
millennium AD. And he did this northern
crusades.
It was pretty brutal. Massacres and
whatnot. And he converted a lot of
people forcibly to Christianity. So,
Christianity the conversion of people to
Christianity became this great
pan-European project of the church.
And over time
various parts of Europe were converted
to Christianity. The further you were
from Rome, the longer it took for the
conversion to happen. So, the Vikings
were doing raids in in in
the British Isles from the
8th to 11th centuries. and it ended with
the defeat of Harald the Hardrada in
1066 AD.
And after that, the Vikings became
Christianized.
Their great tree Yggdrasil was was cut
down. Uppsala was vandalized. The temple
in Uppsala was vandalized destroyed, I'm
sure, replaced with a church. And you
know, it was all brutal.
Now,
Russia as a nation
has a history of maybe a thousand years.
Yeah, with the Kievan Rus, who were of
Viking origin.
And
when did they become Christian, the
Kievan Rus?
Probably about uh
thousand years or 900 years ago. Were
they already Christian by the time
Probably
800 900 years before today. And there
are parts of Russia where Christianity
came only in the last 2 300 years.
And there are parts of Russia where
people still practice, [clears throat]
let's say,
hybrid Christianity, Christianity with
very old pre-Christian traditions
intermixed, yeah?
And the form of Christianity you have in
Russia is is is Orthodox Christianity,
which is which is very similar to the
Greek form of Christianity.
Which is Orthodox Christianity.
So, it's been a process. And it's not
like Russia became Christian nation like
that in all at once. Various parts of
Russia became were were converted to
Christianity by force in various
centuries.
And there were people, you know, who
were burned alive because they would not
convert to Christianity. That happened
what, four five six hundred years before
today. So, it's been a process,
a long
process over the past
roughly 900 or thousand years.
And still,
even today, there are some Christians
who are recent Christians who recent
converts, and they still
practice elements of their pre-Christian
culture, you know?
Uh
There is this god called Triglav.
Triglav.
Tri gla
glove god.
Slavic mythology, Triglav.
So, Triglav in mythology is a
three-headed god.
Okay.
>> [laughter]
>> What are the names of the three heads?
Um
Let's see.
Vision vision vision.
Okay, in Indo-European mythology, these
dark gods have a vision problem. Odin,
Velenus, Varuna. Who is Varuna?
>> [laughter]
>> As you can see, Triglav,
Slavic god.
Three-headed god. So, the the this god
Triglav essentially is Brahma, Vishnu,
and Shiva.
That's what he is.
And
>> [clears throat]
>> this god in was worshipped until pretty
recently in some parts of Russia. So,
it's been a long process, all right?
Uh Fast Snail says, "Musk attributes his
son's name to S. Chandrasekhar
Subramanian Chandrasekhar." Which son?
He's got lots of sons, right? He's got
like 11 12 kids.
I'm not sure which son it could be,
but interesting.
Musk Subramanian Chandrasekhar. Let's
see. Let's Let's Google it.
Uh Elon Musk son
dra dra
Let us see.
Shivon. Okay, Shi Shivon
his his
partner Shivon Zilis,
who is half Indian.
Okay, one of their twins has the middle
name Shekhar,
honoring Subramanian Chandrasekhar.
Okay. Okay, interesting. Fantastic.
Interesting.
Yeah, so so his
So, he has two children with this lady,
right? Shivon Zilis.
Shivon Zilis, I believe her mother was
Indian.
So, she's half Indian. And yeah, okay.
So, one of their kids has the middle
name Shekhar. Okay, interesting.
Aries Manticore says,
"Um I think something interesting is
happening across Europe and Asia.
Christianity is creeping back slowly
within the Gen Z men, and Gen Z
hyperliberalism is increasing among the
women. Engineered
Uh
engineered as well as a reaction. Look,
what's happening in Europe Forget about
the US for now for for a minute. Let's
talk about Europe.
In Europe, what's happening is that
there is an invasion that's being
engineered of Europe. An invasion of
Europe by people by young military age
males who come from specific nations and
who have a specific religion. That
invasion of Europe is being engineered
by the European Union.
And some nations who that don't want to
accept these immigrants, they have to
pay protection money.
Protection money essentially to
Brussels.
Some of multiple millions of dollars
every year
so that they don't have to accept
migrants. So, the immigration is
horribly damaging to European societies.
And if a nation doesn't want the
immigration, they have to pay money to
Brussels, which is like paying
the local goonda
so that the goonda doesn't come and beat
you up. That sort of thing.
So, that's what's happening. Now, most
nations in the EU, they have they are
being forced to
accept this this immigration. And this
immigration is causing
a reaction in European society. And the
males, young males, are getting
radicalized.
And they
That's why they are going back to
Christianity.
Right? Gen Z men, Gen Z young men, etc.
And hyperliberalism is increasing among
women. I think, you know, men and women,
they have very different psychologies,
very different uh
um the way they see the world, etc. It's
It's pretty different for men and women.
So, maybe
maybe this is women are more susceptible
to liberalism. I'm not sure what it is,
but it looks like that, yeah. So,
there's this polarization of society
that's happening. Men are becoming more
radicalized. They're becoming more more
traditional. They are going back to
Christianity.
And women are becoming hyperliberal,
that sort of thing. And maybe in the US
also you you are seeing more of that
now. Now. Uh now that Biden the Biden
regime is over and Trump is back,
and Trump is more of a conservative,
and now that this wokism is now kind of
on the back burner in the US to to a
certain extent,
it is you are seeing this resurgence of
of of slightly more traditional values
in at least in some sections of society.
Mainly among young men. Yeah, so
partly engineered, partly backlash, and
partly
partly natural.
Narendra Reddy says, "What's with recent
rise in hate on Indians online?" We've
discussed this so many times.
Um
It's engineered, right?
It's been engineered since February
2022.
In February 2022,
Russia launched the special military
operation on Ukraine. And the West, the
US, expected India
to tow its line.
They expected India to participate in US
and Western sanctions on Russia. They
expected India India to condemn the
invasion and and uh
you know, decouple from Russia. And
India did the exact opposite.
And that's why there was this big
outlash backlash against India. This
outpouring of hatred towards India,
which was manufactured on social media.
It starts with all the big media outlets
like the BBC, like this like the CNN,
New York Times,
Washington Post putting out daily
articles castigating India and raking
India over the coals. Then you have
think tanks like Rand
Rand Rand Corpora- corporation. And god
knows how many think tanks all putting
out anti-India articles.
And then there was this
concerted campaign on social media of
demonizing India and and you know, all
kinds of
nasty things about India being said by
bots, anonymous accounts.
And that has continued since 2022. It's
been what, more than three three and a
half years.
So, over time, that that that compounds.
And that's why it is now very
fashionable really fashionable
fashionable to to hate on Indians and be
racist against Indians online. And then
you have the Chinese and the Pakistanis
piling in.
So, you have all these,
you know,
accounts on on X and whatnot, which are
super hateful towards Indian Indians.
And now that X is making it mandatory to
show your region, you will see all those
accounts based in so-called South Asia.
So, you can choose your country or
region. If you don't want to see say
Pakistan, you have to say South Asia.
So, when it says South Asia, it's either
Bangladesh or Pakistan.
So, it's a bunch of Pakistani and
Bangladeshi accounts who have been
masquerading as Indians, who are now
saying they're South Asians. And they're
all anti-India accounts. And the Chinese
also are involved in this. So, that's
why there is this massive hate against
Indians online.
Neil says, "Your thoughts on three uh
Atlas alien possibilities?" I don't
believe it's an alien thing.
I have seen no evidence of that. None
whatsoever.
Rahul says, "Shed some light on Devadasi
propaganda." I don't know sufficient I
don't have sufficient information about
this.
What I know is that these were temple
dancers. And I eventually
some kind of distortion of the
historical facts happened because of the
missionaries in the British, but I don't
know what the details are, so I can't
say, sorry.
Aries Manticore says, "You need not be
discouraged about the horrendous
education system and declining culture.
Our civilization will evolve and survive
in its own unique way by sheer necessity
enforced by the public." I really hope
so.
I am a very optimistic person. It is
very hard to discourage me. So, I will
follow your instructions and I will not
be discouraged. So, thank you so much
for
for the encouragement and for reminding
me not to be discouraged. Thank you very
much.
Ankita ji says,
uh question by Annamalai uh in in
Yamaraj
Sydney attack, what's going on? How to
stop such attacks in India?
Sydney attack, it happened today, right?
Um Bondi Beach, an iconic beach in
Sydney. Sydney, probably Sydney.
And there was some kind of Jewish
Jewish
I don't know. Festival was it?
Some kind of Jewish event was there at
the beach. And it looks like a bunch of
Pakistanis came with
with with
with weapons, rifles or something. And
they shot a
apparently shot a lot of people. I don't
know how many people have been shot. I
don't know how many casualties may or
may not have happened. Let's let's
quickly take a look at what's happened.
Yeah, let's see.
Bondi Beach
uh beach attack.
Attack. Okay, so do we have Okay, there
we have this. It's already there,
Wikipedia article. Okay, Hanukkah
celebration hosted by the Chabad of
Bondi.
And 12 people were killed. Good lord.
Including one of the two shooters. The
second shooter is in custody, okay. Do
the shooters have names? Let's see.
Okay, we know what Bondi Beach is.
Two men pump action shotguns, bolt
action rifle, red dot sight.
One of the shooters blah blah blah,
response casualties, assailants
two men dressed etc. Killing one gunman,
another one is shot and taken critical
condition. What are their names? What
are their names?
What are their names?
I would like to know the names.
Um various nations, Prime Minister Modi
offered condolences.
Um beach shooting.
I'm pretty sure at least one of these
two
gunmen
was of Pakistani origin.
So, yeah. Okay. So, that's what's
happened. Looks like uh
there have been casualties, sadly.
Um
What's going on? Well,
there is this great hatred towards Jews
from people who belong to certain
countries.
And that's why this has happened.
Right?
And um the Western world, see Australia
is part of the Western world even though
it's in Oceania. The Western world has
been very
somehow likes these people very much.
People
from certain countries, especially
Pakistan.
So, they are importing them and this is
what this is the consequence of that.
So, that that's what's going on. It's
it's terrible, it's tragic that these
gunmen have shot people.
Uh how to stop such attacks in India?
By being constantly vigilant.
There's no solution, no other solution.
Be constantly vigilant.
That's the only thing.
Sadly.
Vinayak Naik says, a big admirer of
Nala. Thank you so much, sir. Thank you
very much. Could you please share your
insights on Odisha's history,
particularly the role role of the
Khandayat community in shaping it? I
don't know anything, sadly, about the
Khandayat community. There are
thousands of these very interesting
communities all across India with their
own rich and deep history
going back, I don't know how many
centuries, how many thousands of years.
But
I I don't know about this particular
community, so I can't say. But yeah,
Odisha's history, I've spoken about this
at great length in on multiple
occasions. Great history, glorious
history of Odisha.
Odisha,
it is Odisha, it's the people of Odisha
that
Indianized
Southeast Asia, that brought Indian that
took Indian culture to Southeast Asia.
Uh the people of Odisha, the people of
Kalinga were trading with Suvarnabhumi,
which is Southeast Asia,
from at least
3,000 years before today. At least 1,000
BC, most likely before that.
And to trade, they had to cross the
so-called Bay of Bengal, the Kalinga
Kalinga Sagar.
You can't cross that
with small boats. They they used big
ships for that. So, that once again is
an example of how ancient our seafaring,
our maritime traditions are. India is
the world's oldest maritime
civilization.
So, the people of Odisha of of Kalinga
would cross the the ocean, go to
Suvarnabhumi, trade with them, and this
happened for centuries and centuries and
centuries. Eventually, the whole of
Southeast Asia
became Indianized. They absorbed our
culture, our religion, our
civilizational traditions, not through
force, but just by constant interaction.
Yeah. So, if you had Hinduism all across
Southeast Asia, Indonesia, etc., it's
thanks to the great people of Odisha.
So, that's just
one small aspect of the history of
Kalinga. So much more, of course.
Uh Honey Sharma says, "21 million gave
CAT this year and won't get
21 M. Okay, you are 21 male. You're
male, you're 21 years old. I gave the
CAT this year and won't get the college
I desire. I'll give it next week. If I
make it then, I'll be 25 when I'm out of
college. Then education loan, want to
travel the world before getting married
married. I'll be 28 by then. Is it too
old?
Mm. This this is the dilemma everybody
has. Young All young people have.
So, you gave CAT this year, did not get
the college you want you desired. You
will give it next year.
If you get it by next year, then you'll
be 25 by the time you're out of the
college.
Then there's an education loan that you
will have take for going through
college. Then you want to travel the
world while getting before getting
married.
So, let's say you travel
the world for 3 years, you'll be 28. And
then by by then, is it too old to get
married? I would say
Look, let's say hopefully you get the
college you desire next year.
You're 25 by the time you're out of the
college. I would say you you get married
and travel the world. I know it will
cost more.
But I it'll be a better experience,
perhaps. Or maybe you have Okay, it's up
to you.
>> [laughter]
>> It's up to you what you want to do with
life.
Is 28 too old to get married?
A little old, I would say. But there are
people who get married in the in their
30s and have good lives. So, it it
depends.
From my perspective, I urge all young
people to get married at the earliest.
Uh before 25.
When you will be for in your 40s, you
will realize I was I was right. At this
time, you might think I'm not.
So, I would urge everybody to get
married by the time you're 25 or
something. But if you want to get
married by 28, I don't think it's too
late. It's entirely up to you.
So, all the best, sir. Do well.
Yeah, I hope you get the college you
desire next year.
And uh
go follow your dreams and ambitions and
do well in life. All the best. I don't
think 28 is too late, right?
Okay. Hrithik Pawar says, "Is it is it
possible for humans to destroy Earth
into debris?" No.
We don't have that power yet. We don't
have
the Death Star like
like in Star Trek. It's not possible for
humans to destroy the Earth into bits.
No, we don't have the power.
Rajat says, "We have we have DRDO We
have GTRE, the Gas Turbine Research
Establishment. We have DRDO uh Defense
Research Development and Development
Organization. We have Hindustan
Aeronautics Limited. What has stopped
India from manufacturing its own jet in
the past 40 years? We are begging for
engines.
Where is the technology gap?"
Yeah.
We have all these fantastic
organizations. What have they been
doing?
Some of the blame lies with the
organizations.
government.
For example, if you see DRDO.
DRDO was founded what, 1958?
It was founded the same year as DARPA, D
A R P A, DARPA. DARPA is the United
States version of DRDO.
And DARPA has given the US some of the
greatest technological breakthroughs in
human history.
Stealth technology and so much more.
DARPA.
DARPA was founded in 1958, DRDO also
1958. DARPA today has about double the
budget of DRDO. Not 10 times, not 100
times, only double.
So, DRDO has a similar budget as DARPA.
But DARPA has 150 employees or people
working for DARPA. 150.
DRDO has about 20,000, 30,000.
That's the difference.
And out of those 20,000, 30,000
employees that DRDO has, 5,000 are
scientists. So, why are 25,000
non-scientists working for DRDO?
This is how we sabotage ourselves.
I don't know what DRDO was Okay, let's
find Let's Let's Let's do this right
now. Yeah, DRDO.
DRDO.
Um let's see. DRDO
founded which year? 1958. See, I was
right. 1958. What is the budget?
Annual budget is 3.2 billion for
DRDO. And I was right.
30,000 employees with 5,000 scientists.
So, what are 25,000 non-scientists doing
with these with this money that is
scientific budget the
R&D budget. This is how we mess
everything up. Why are 25,000
non-scientists leeching off that money?
This is the problem in India. We mess
everything up by design. Everything is
designed wrong.
And then then how will anything happen?
And then you have administrators
and and managers and bureaucrats telling
each employee what to do. They will
report to one guy who will report to
another guy who will report to another
guy. This this detailed pyramidal
structure
hierarchical structure. In DARPA,
there's no hierarchy.
150 people
work for DARPA and they get the entirety
of the budget. No no not a single
non-scientist get gets any of the budget
of DARPA.
Let's see DARPA also since since since
since since we saw DRDO.
So, when was DARPA established? I just
checked DRDO.
DARPA was established when?
1958. See, I was right once again.
How many employees do they have? 220.
Okay, not 150, 220.
Annual budget 4.122 billion, which is
like double roughly of DRDO.
But
think about what DARPA has given to the
US. The technological breakthroughs
DARPA has given to the US. And think
about what DRDO has done.
Has DRDO since 1958 produced a single
groundbreaking
world-class technology? No.
All we are doing is trying to replicate
what the West did 20 30 years ago.
That's all.
And
it's not like the scientists are bad,
the engineers are bad.
They can only do what
they are told to do. They can't take up
a project they want to take up because
it's good for the country.
They can only work on projects that are
sanctioned from all the way up.
And that vision comes from politicians.
So, look, these are the problems. And
that's why we are still begging for
engines. You see the problems?
The problems are designed into the
system.
If there are problems, they are the
problems are part of the design.
Whoever designed this, they introduced
problems knowingly into the system.
And we are just continuing that all year
after year after year, decade after
decade.
What are we doing? I just don't get it.
Okay, Animesh says, "Any great movies
you'd recommend that come to mind?"
Any great movies? I should make list of
movie recommendations, maybe 50 movies
or something.
Great movies. Look,
some of the greatest movies of all time
are from the 20th century.
In compared to today's movies, you may
think it's these are quite slow. For
example, The Good, the Bad and the Ugly.
One of the greatest movies I've ever
seen in our entire life. The Good, the
Bad and the Ugly. Good God, what a great
movie it is. But you may find it slow.
You want action and explosions every 2
minutes, it's not for you.
But if you want a true experience,
The Good, the Bad and the Ugly, The
Seven Samurai,
uh movies by Akira Akira Kurosawa,
Japanese director.
When I was a small kid,
I had this this movie came out.
Kagemusha.
I never saw it, but I I should see it.
I'm not sure how good it was or
but it's a Kurosawa movie. So, movies by
Sergio Leone,
um movies that star Bud Spencer and
Terence Hill, outstanding movies from
the 1960s, 70s, perhaps even 80s they
were they were getting old.
Bud Spencer, Terence Hill were Italian
actors actually.
Um I love Jim Carrey movies. I love
comedy movies. The Mask,
um The Godfather one and two,
the Star Wars trilogy, the original one,
not the later one.
Um
The greatest science fiction movie in
the past 20 years, 25 years is
Interstellar. I hated Arrival. Arrival
is a is a art movie trying to pretend to
be a science fiction movie. Garbage. I
didn't like it at all. Not garbage,
well-made, very cinematic, very
you know,
well-produced movie etc., but didn't do
it anything for me.
I loved um
Interstellar. Great.
Um
so, maybe I should make a separate list
for that, yeah?
Aries Manticore says, "I think they are
geoengineering a radical Muslim
population in the West on purpose
to radicalize their own citizens towards
soft authoritarianism. National
Socialism is rising fast, especially in
the United States."
Uh that could potentially perhaps uh
explain some of what's happening in the
Western world, in Europe, in the United
States.
Yeah, maybe maybe.
Geoengineering. Maybe it's social
engineering more than geoengineering,
but it has geo the geo element too. Of
course, it's happening over a wide
geographical um
expanse, let's say. Indeed.
Aries Manticore says, "Hi sir, lately
you seem exhausted. Please take care." I
I seem exhausted? See, lately I've been
doing very extended sessions.
Usually, I used to do these two-hour
sessions. Now you can see it's 2 hours
53 minutes. You speak
speak speak for three, four I've I've
done four-hour sessions. I've done
six-hour session.
I did one almost nine-hour session.
So, you do those very lengthy session
sessions sitting in one place, you're
going to
be a little tired eventually. But
anyway, thank you so much for the
concern. I do take care.
And uh yeah, thank you.
>> [clears throat]
>> Abhinav says, "Why doesn't the US force
all its vassals like the EU, Japan,
South Korea to impose
uh sanctions on India if it wants to
contain India's rise?" Well, have you
heard of Mexico?
Mexico has recently imposed tariffs on
India. Let's see.
They will do it in a phased manner, not
not all at once. You see,
Mexico
tariff on India. There we have it.
Check it out.
Mexico has imposed 50% tariffs on Indian
goods. Would you believe it? Mexico is
Mexico is a friendly nation.
Nothing explains this except that Mexico
has been pressurized into doing this by
the Trump regime.
So,
anyway, it's not like we have a huge
amount of trade with Mexico, but you
know,
this is what the US is doing.
It's not like Mexico suddenly decided
I'll impose tariffs on on India. Mexico
and India have friendly relationship,
good relationship. The Americans, the
Trump regime have forced Mexico to do
this.
So, they may do this vis-a-vis other
nations also. They may ask European
nations to do that.
They may ask Japan, South Korea perhaps.
So, wherever India has significant
substantial amount of trade, they could
force their vassals to do that in those
cases, yeah?
Rajat says,
"What does What What does it mean that
identical fermions cannot have the same
state? How does it affect
atoms in matter?"
See,
in quantum mechanics, there's something
called quantum statistics.
And there are
there's Bose-Einstein statistics and
Fermi-Dirac statistics.
Particles, so you know, fundamental
particles or subatomic particles that
that that follow Bose-Einstein
statistics are called bosons. And
particles that follow Fermi-Dirac
statistics are called fermions. Bosons
have
integer spins, spin What spin?
Well, when we think of spin, we think of
this, right? This, that. Well, you can
think of it that way, but quantum spin
is something different. It's not exactly
particle spinning, but yeah, let's let's
think of it that way. So,
bosons have integer spin.
And and fermions have half integer spin.
And
fermions follow the Pauli exclusion
principle.
And we don't know where it comes from,
what causes it. Okay?
But what the Pauli exclusion principle
says that, you know, you have energy
levels in
bound states in quantum mechanics.
And
the Pauli exclusion principle says that
no two identical fermions can
occupy the same
energy level in a quantum system.
So, think of it as a quantum system like
let's say let's say the hydrogen atom.
The hydrogen atom has
two elements. One is the nucleus, which
is simply one proton.
And the other one is the electron that
orbits the proton. Think of it
very crudely and incorrectly as the the
moon orbiting the earth. It's not like
that, but you can think of it like that
just to just for the sake of, you know,
understanding.
So, that's what you have. A proto
electron going along going around
neutron about proton. Now, the electron
can occupy various energy levels.
Now, if you have a more a complex atom
with let's say 50 electrons or whatever,
then each electron will have a certain
energy state.
And electrons
are fermions.
Protons, neutrons, electrons are
fermions. So, electrons
if it is in an excited state, higher
energy state, then it's going to the
it's going to affect the the mass and
the energy configuration of the atom.
And the point is that
when it comes to the lowest energy
state in the in the atom, it's going to
be only one electron that's going to be
there.
So, the point is the
what this says, what the Pauli exclusion
principle what the effect it has is that
matter occupies space.
Okay? So, when you try to squeeze an
atom,
there's going to be a pressure outwards
that comes from the Pauli exclusion
principle.
Because no matter how hard you squeeze,
the Pauli exclusion exclusion principle
ensures that
no two identical fermions can be in the
same
uh state, the same energy state, which
is why matter is spaced out. And that's
why
matter occupies space. You see?
You see, why does this ball occupy
space? Because of the Pauli exclusion
principle. Why do our physical bodies
occupy actual space?
The Pauli exclusion principle. And you
can make jokes out of it, but I will not
do those here.
Okay, Abhinav Singh, thank you very
much, sir. You did this yesterday also.
You gifted memberships. Thank you so
much. Thank you to everybody who's doing
this. Abhinav Singh ji, thank you very
much for gifting
memberships to our viewers.
That is so kind of you. I really
appreciate that, sir.
Rahul Lak says, "Have you read or
watched The Expanse?" I haven't watched
it or or read it. Brief review review
comments opinion on the science and
politics of it. I haven't watched it.
I I would love to watch so many of these
science fiction another series, you
know, but I just don't have the time.
So, I haven't seen it. I haven't watched
it. I haven't read it.
So, I won't be able to comment on that,
but I've heard it's interesting. Well,
let's see what is the IMDb rating of
that, The Expanse. Let's see.
Expanse. So, The Expanse came out in
which year?
2019. It's got 8.5 on IMDb, which is
outstanding.
Does it have a diverse cast?
Does it have a strong female lead? I
don't know about that, but it looks like
it's interesting.
Uh but I haven't had the time to watch
it. It's available on Prime Video,
apparently. Okay?
Haven't read it or seen it or read it.
Sorry.
Uh Neal Singha is a new member. Thank
you so much, sir, for becoming a member.
Let us all welcome
Neal Singha ji to
the membership of the channel. Thank you
very much, sir. Appreciate it very much.
Biju Saikia says, "Is China hiding its
economic crisis?" I don't know.
I'm not sure.
Um
Is China hiding
an economic crisis?
Does it have a crisis? See, its GDP
doesn't seem to be growing very fast
anymore. It's stuck at 18 trillion
dollars roughly thereabouts.
Um
But is there a major crisis that's
brewing in the Chinese economy? Is it Is
it hiding that? I am not quite sure
about that.
Not quite sure about that.
Uh Critical Returns Returns says,
"Finite Hilbert space imply time and
that heat death?" I'm not sure Hilbert
space has something to do with time.
Um
The time is is Yeah, the question
essentially is about time, right? When
does time begin? When does time end?
That's what you're asking. And uh
the heat death of the universe, does
time end there?
Yeah, we don't know about time. Time is
the biggest mystery.
And even in quantum mechanics that
you're referring to,
uh time is an external parameter.
It's an external parameter. It's a
classical parameter. It's not a quantum
parameter. It's not an observable.
Is it an observable?
Position and momentum are observables,
right? Time is not an observable. No.
Time is an external parameter. It's a
classical parameter. So, time quantum
mechanics cannot explain time. It does
not It's not in a position to explain
time right now. There are some theories
that say that, you know, time
emerges. It's an emergent phenomenon. It
emerges from emerges from quantum
entanglement, etc., but that's
theory. There's no actual experimental
evidence of that. So, we don't have an
answer about time right now. Does time
end at heat death? Does it have
something to do with
you know, Hilbert space?
Um
No, we don't have the answers.
Rajat says, "As asked by you, Vedantic
definition of consciousness is
it It's that which is different from
things which are known
and unknown
to mind."
It's that which is different
from things which are known and unknown
to mind.
It's I I first thought it's
philosophical, but it's the most
scientific answer.
Scientific.
Okay, I'll think about it. Is it Is it
philosophical or is it scientific?
A scientific definition of something
means it's it's it's something that's
physical.
See, in in science,
let's come to the subset of science that
we're dealing with with with physics.
In physics,
something When you say something, that
something has to be observable,
quantifiable, measurable.
Now, is consciousness observable,
quantifiable, measurable measurable?
It's not. So, I'm not sure this is a
scientific or or physical answer.
This is definitely philosophical. It's
an interesting It's an interesting
definition.
It's that which is different from things
which are known and unknown to mind.
But when we are dealing with knowns and
unknowns, it's not very very scientific.
That's how I see it. I'll I'll I'll have
to think about it a little more because
this is the very interesting definition.
I'll I'll revisit this. But well, thank
you for sharing this. This is definitely
interesting, very interesting.
I will
spend some time thinking about this.
Maybe I'll get back to you about this in
a future episode. Thank you.
Okay.
Prabhu to P says, "Thought on Quest for
Love book."
Why Indian people are not responsible
independent like we see in other Asian
countries, although all colonized?
Quest for Love book. What is that? Quest
for Love book. Let's see.
Quest for Love book. What is that?
Good
God.
Oh God, I'm not sure this is my going to
be my favorite thing to read ever.
>> [snorts]
>> Anikya Lucas.
Who is this?
Is this a real thing?
Anikya Lucas is a blah etc.
Oh God, this will be
harrowing to read.
I don't think I am going to read this
thing. This is Look,
uh I like as much positivity in my life
as possible. I know
you have to read and learn about the
world and all, but I don't think this is
something I would ever want to read.
So, yeah, I
I haven't read it. I was not aware of
this. And I don't think I'm going to
read this.
It's not what I need at this point in
time or ever.
I know these things exist and there's a
lot of horrible stuff in the world.
So sadly.
Yeah, but um
whoever that lady is, I I
sorry for whatever she went through. I
hope I wish her well.
But uh I'm not going to be reading that.
Yeah, sorry. Uh why are Indian people
not responsible independent like we see
in other Asian countries?
Even though all were colonized.
Different
different forms of colonization,
different time periods of colonization.
When we say colonization, we are we mean
foreign occupation.
Now, India
has been under foreign occupation
for a thousand years.
Okay?
The Turkic occupation starts on the
northwestern fringes of India, and it
eventually came all the way into other
parts of India. So, all of India was not
under foreign occupation a thousand
years ago, but it starts about a
thousand years ago.
And then further north you go, the more
mentally colonized people are. This is
something many people will observe.
But not necessarily that the further
south you go, the less mentally
colonized people are.
It depends on so many different factors.
But when
a culture is under foreign occupation
for a thousand years,
it's going to have deep scars. It's
going to leave leave behind deep deep
scars.
And
we
have introduced a very poisonous thing
in our system,
which is the
colonial
education system that was
crafted by the English.
And we still continue that. So, we have
been
we have been
indoctrinating and brainwashing
generation after generation of Indians
for about
since about what?
The 1860s, 1870s. And we're still doing
that today. It's been what? 150, 160,
160 years. More than 160 years. So,
that's why generation after generation
the same system is being used to
brainwash and mentally colonize and
indoctrinate our people. That's why
we are so
uh the way we are. Incapable of thinking
independently.
Indians are like goddamn sheep.
The moment you you you show independent
thinking, they will all descend upon you
with their
parroting the thoughts from their
teachers and textbooks.
It's it's so
sad to see Indians
relying on dogma. Dogma, as like Steve
Jobs once said in some address, dogma is
nothing but the product of other
people's thinking.
Dogma is the the result of other
people's thinking. Every idea that most
Indians express is the result of other
people's thinking. They don't have
original ideas and thoughts.
That's what the system has done to
Indians. That's why they are like this.
The system is designed to turn Indians
into zombies in this manner.
And this is what we what we
tom-tom as the great wonderful new
education policy.
Yes, there have been some little small
changes that are good. This change of
syllabus, etc., but the overall system
is still based on rote rote memorization
and absolute obedience.
And third-rate teachers. What will
change? Nothing.
King Ritwik says, "Middle-aged people
are taking trips to Ladakh and Sikkim
because of hype of mountains. They
suffer from breathlessness. Precautions
they should take."
Um
You have to be careful going to Ladakh.
Sikkim is not that high. Ladakh is super
super high.
Uh what precautions do you have to take?
First of all, if you are a smoker, don't
go to Ladakh. You will not regret it.
Okay?
Secondly,
uh you will need
to ensure that you you have good car-
cardiovascular health,
good lung capacity,
and um you need to have good endurance.
If you have these qualities, then you
will be able to
uh survive Ladakh and tolerate the the
high altitude. See, what happens at high
altitude is that there is less oxygen.
So, your cardiovascular
efficiency needs to be high in order to
be to able to to be able to tolerate
this. When you're at high altitudes,
even your vehicles perform poorly
because your vehicles need oxygen for
combustion.
So, if you have a four-wheel drive SUV
that performs at a you know, has a
certain horsepower rating at sea level,
you take it to Ladakh, it's going to be
like 1/3 of that or something. I mean,
it's going to be way less than what it
is at sea level. It's going to when you
drive, you'll feel it's much weaker than
what it is.
The same applies to us, human beings,
our our respiration.
So, my
the precautions you should take is if
you are a smoker, don't go to Ladakh.
If you have
any breathing issues, don't go to
Ladakh.
If you are reasonably healthy,
but you're overweight or whatever, then
I'm not saying lose weight. Just
you know,
work on your endurance. Go for, you
know, practice jogging like 30 minutes a
day for for a couple of months before
you go to Ladakh. That That should
That should ensure that there's no
issues. If you have diabetes, if you
have any pre-existing health conditions,
I would recommend don't go to Ladakh.
You need to be strong, sturdy, and
healthy to go to Ladakh.
I went
to Ladakh a couple of years ago with
like three young three young guys who
are part of my team.
And one guy who's 20, I'm I'm climbing a
monastery and that guy is like all dizzy
and has to sit down. So, even young
people
will face issues if you are not careful
uh when you go to Ladakh. So, my point
is
so, and and there is this this one pill
I don't remember what it's called, but
you know, if you take that one pill that
that pill, then um
you will not be that susceptible to to
altitude sickness or something. I'm not
sure what the what the pill is called,
but you can look it up. I have never
taken it. But uh yeah, I I think it
helps.
It helps. So, yeah. [clears throat]
Do some research. If you're reasonably
healthy, make sure that, you know, your
endurance is good, your lung power is
good, your cardiovascular system is in
good good shape. Practice jogging 20 30
minutes a day for a couple of months
before you go there. And take the pill.
Um ask your travel agent for what pill
it is or
look it up online, right? All right. All
the best.
Um Anantha Subramanian says, "What key
lessons of history do do most people
miss?" Don't Didn't I take this question
about a couple of hours ago? Same
person, I think.
We've taken this question, sir. We've
we've taken this question. Maybe I'll
I'll
expand upon that upon this in a future
video or something. But yeah, it's
definitely like
it's it's certainly very interesting and
very important
topic.
But I did speak about this a while ago,
couple of hours ago. We are like 3 hours
10 minutes into this episode.
In the first hour or so, I took it.
Okay. Ares Manticore says,
"I came across a mathematical research
focused on proving that the selfish gene
theory to be false.
Will AI be used to accelerate evolution
for say life extension or interstellar
adaptation? What's my take?" Okay.
Selfish gene theory, I haven't read
Dawkins and his work. Is it Dawkins
Richard Dawkins Selfish Gene? Let me
see.
Gene.
Richard Dawkins. Yeah, I am not a big
fan of all this popular science crap. I
haven't read this book. Yeah.
If if I read science, I actually read
research papers and go deeper into
things. Anyway, uh so, I am not sure
about this selfish gene, what the theory
is, what the book is about.
And um so, I won't be able to comment
about that. Now, will AI be used to
accelerate evolution
for various things? Yeah, suddenly.
You can accelerate [clears throat]
evolution
through genetic engineering.
For example, you can create uh
you know, customized babies.
When your baby is an embryo, you can do
some genetic engineering genetic genetic
modification using maybe CRISPR or
something.
And and create a super baby with with
all the best
you know, genetic advantages you can
possibly have through genetic
engineering. And you can use AI to
to you know,
to do genetic engineering better than
you can do it right now.
So, it's definitely going to AI is
definitely going to be used in genetic
engineering
to to
target specific genes and to to
introduce specific traits in your
offspring and future organisms and so
on. It can also also be used for genetic
warfare using gene drives and whatnot.
So,
there's it's going to have all kinds of
applications in genetics, for sure. So,
that when you when you edit your genes
and you pass that on to the next
generation, you are interfering in the
process of of evolution. And you it can
be said that you are selectively
um you you are you are
you're selecting the direction in which
evolution goes.
And you are accelerating the process of
evolution because it would not have
happened naturally. Yeah.
>> [clears throat]
>> Gajapathi Deva says, "Have you read
Delimitation by Professor Desiraju
views?" I have read the book
Delimitation by Professor Desiraju. I've
had him on a podcast in which we have
discussed the book.
My views, I think it's a very good book.
Uh what he what Professor Desiraju
suggests is very good. He's suggesting
that India should He's recommending that
India should have 75 states instead of
the number of states we that we have
today.
I pretty much agree with what he says. I
would take it one step further. I would
say maybe we need to have 100 states.
I'm not sure what is the right number.
75 seems to be a good number.
And that would
have all kinds of benefits like better
governance, better better
administration, a better access to to
power to for for ordinary people
and and so much more, you know? So,
yeah, it's it's a great book. It's a
great um
recommendation.
And it would be great if it happens.
Yeah.
Chirag Yunat says, "I have always
wondered, why do why do rich people and
countries always turn more always turn
socialistic after getting rich and they
want to entrench the same bad behavior
that led them
to being poor?"
Um see,
>> [clears throat]
>> when when do you How does somebody
become How does a society become rich?
A society becomes rich when it is lean,
when it is
deprived of things, and when it is
strongly desirous of of a better
lifestyle, of better living standards,
of better of of better circumstances.
So, when you are in living in hardship,
that's when you have the highest
motivation day after day after day.
You don't need to look for motivation,
it's all around you. You are very
uncomfortable. You are very unhappy. So,
you have the
greatest motivation to to escape that.
So, that's how you work really hard and
you become powerful and rich. Once you
are rich, you become soft. You enjoy the
fruits of your labor.
Subsequent generations don't understand
what the previous generations had to go
through
so that the nation could become rich.
Right?
They are born into
into into luxury. They are born into
into into wealth.
And they think that that's how things
should be. And that's the
That's when
so, they are born into an era where
there are no problems in the nation. No
no real problems in the nation.
But the human mind is such that we seek
some struggle in life to give us
meaning.
Without struggle, life has no meaning.
Without a prob- without problems to
solve, life seems meaningless. So, we
look for problems. Then we look at small
problems, you know,
social stratification, social status,
and some people have less wealth than
us, and we should make everybody equal,
and all that nonsense comes from there.
So, that's what happens. And that's why
we have
imperial cycles. Empires come, rise and
fall, rise and fall, rise and fall.
Always happens
because
of this process. See, and that that's an
issue.
>> [clears throat]
>> But it's it's part of human nature.
Looks like we can't escape that.
Okay.
Kiki Sushant, well, thank you very much,
sir, for your contribution. Really
really appreciate that. Thank you, sir.
Fast Snail says, "I admire how you can
switch switch context
and answer questions spontaneously. I
need some tips for job interviews when I
when I fail to convince, but I know the
answer." You have to practice.
You know the answer, but you haven't
practiced answering it.
You have to
first of all,
you need to first of all, anticipate all
the googlies they can throw at you.
In American parlance, they say curve
balls.
In Indian parlance, we'll say googlies.
You have to be able to anticipate all
the
tricks they can spring upon you as
interviewers.
And then you need to practice.
Have somebody play the role of
interviewer, give them a list of all the
tough questions, all the questions you
expect, all the unexpected questions,
and have them interview you over and
over and over again. And practice your
delivery.
Practice giving the right answer. You
know the answer, but maybe the first
time you did not give it properly in the
practice session.
So, then think about what how you could
have done better. Then do another
practice session in which you do a
better job. And you do it over and over
again. Maybe 10 20 times you do the the
process of the mock interviews.
Then you're going to be confident.
And ask your friends not to be very
friendly to you. Ask them to be, you
know, that sort of thing. So, put
yourself in that situation
in in in
in a situation that would be very
similar to the actual interview. That's
what you do.
And in case you don't have friends who
who will do this for you,
well, practice in front of a mirror.
In case you don't have privacy, do it at
night or whatever. Find a way. Go to the
forest and talk to the trees like
Abraham Lincoln used to do. So, the
point is practice, practice, practice.
Then it becomes natural and spontaneous.
All right. All the best, sir.
Fast snail.
Uh Prashant Sharma says, "Bondi Beach
incident, what will leftists say now?
Terrible, horrible, tragic,
ghastly, unacceptable incident." I have
no idea what the leftists will say. The
leftists will still say that let's
import more Pakistanis. I'm sure.
Australian leftists, right?
Um and leftists across the world will
say that you know what, Pakistan is
still a peaceful and nice nation.
So, they will not change their attitude,
their behavior, their approach. But we
know what Pakistan is. Looks like at
least one of the gunmen was a Pakistani.
Looks like that. So, my question is why
is the government of Australia importing
Pakistanis, and especially Pakistanis
who are
prone to such
such
activities,
actions. I don't get it. Terrible.
Horrible. So, it's it's terrible that
this thing has happened. Um
unfortunately, it looks like there have
been some casualties. Just just
bad, terrible, avoidable.
Hyphen says, "I grew up in India. I
moved to the UK when I was 18. I'm a
truck driver in the UK, but not
comfortable driving in India anymore.
Always wondered how over traffic and
driving problems can be solved. Look,
so you drive in the UK.
In the UK, in any Western country,
you're going to have traffic rules that
are followed.
You're going to have high-quality road
surfaces.
No
bumps and craters and potholes. You
won't have that. It's It's unheard of
even in the countries and countryside.
And um
for people that that
break the the traffic rules, etc.,
there's going to There's always
consequences,
right?
In India, we don't have that. In India,
when you go for the uh driving test to
get your license, they're going to
grill you over the rules, traffic rules,
and driving rules, and whatnot,
regulations, and so on.
The moment you get your license, you can
forget about that because nobody follows
any traffic rules.
Go outside of your house, no matter
where you are in India,
and if you are wondering what the
problem in India is, go out and look at
the traffic. Does anybody follow traffic
rules? Nobody does. So, that's the
number one problem. There's no
enforcement. It's not like people don't
want to follow traffic rules. It's that
people over generations have not
been policed and enforced. So, the
traffic rules have not been enforced.
So, the just people just drive. And yet,
you don't have those many accidents that
you would expect because
what
what what reasons. So,
firstly, there is no enforcement of
traffic rules.
Secondly,
you have terrible roads in lots of many
parts of India, right?
So, um
how can all these problems be solved?
First,
through proper enforcement
of the rules. Second, consequences for
those who break the rules. Third, by
improving the surfaces, the the quality
of the roads by having a uniform
standard across the country, and a high
standard, not a low standard,
right?
The solutions are pretty simple.
But enforce But implementing those,
well,
it can be implemented in a in over the
across the country in 2 3 years.
But looks like it's not high on the list
of priorities
for the powers that be.
UMX Glow Allah ha ha says, "How is
air quality index calculated? Is the air
really bad that bad here?" I'm not sure
how the air quality index is calculated.
I I calculated. I have never looked into
it. So, I could start looking into it,
but it'll take time.
But I'm sure there's a
you know, a standard way of
calculating it.
Is the air really that bad in India? Not
all across India.
You go to different parts of India,
you'll have different kinds of air
quality. But yeah, in certain parts of
India like
during the winter time in northern
India, there's terrible air quality. You
can see that.
I mean, whenever I land in Delhi when
it's in winter, starting from what,
October, November, typically November
onwards all the way to February,
the moment you land,
before you land, you can see it, you
know? When you're flying, you can see
there's a there's a clear separate layer
of haze all the way down. And above that
about 10 km up, there is blue sky.
So, once the aircraft reaches an
altitude of of 8 9 km above the surface,
that's when you see that you are above
the layer of haze.
That layer of haze is just just smoke.
And when you are flying above the Delhi
region
in the darkness, you can see fires
dotting the landscape. Fires that are
lit by
farmers, apparently.
So, there are all these issues, you
know?
And even in other parts of India, if you
go to southern part of India, eastern,
western, you'll see a lot of haze and
smoke and all that.
And there are well, various reasons for
that. India is a developing country.
Lots of vehicles, lots of people.
That's why there's going to be all these
combustion engines that are burning
churning out
um you know,
hydrocarbon emissions of various kinds.
So, yeah, the air quality is definitely
Even China has had all these problems,
but they've solved it for Beijing. Not
all across China, but for Beijing, they
solved it before the 2008 Olympics. So,
it can be done. But if you're if you are
a developing nation, if you're growing
very
rapidly, pollution is going to be an
issue. There's nothing you can do much
about it, you know?
Okay.
Tejas is a new member. Thank you very
much, Tejas. Good to have you as a
member. Let's all welcome Tejas
into the channel channel's membership.
Thank you very much.
Honey Sharma says, "I meant I'll be 25
when I get out of college and 28 when
I'm free with my educational loans.
Then travel the world for 2 years and
then get married."
Traveling with a partner is too
expensive, I guess. Otherwise, meet me,
please. Okay, you'll be 28 when you are
done
with repaying the education loans, and
then you want to travel the world for 2
years. So, you will get married when you
are 30.
Well, I suppose it can work.
You get married when you're 30. By the
time you're 50, you will have
maybe kids that are a kid that's 18 if
you wait for a couple of years to have a
kid.
The the thing about the reason One of
the reasons I say you should get married
early
is because you need a lot of energy to
raise kids.
Kids will take a lot of a lot out of
you. The older you are, the less energy
you have.
If you have kids at the age of 40,
they'll grow up If you have one kid at
the age of 40, that kid will become 18
or 20 when you're 60.
You're going to have to go through a lot
in that time period. But if you have a
kid when you're 22,
by the time you're 40, your kid is grown
up.
Then you can do whatever you want life.
So, that's why having kids early is the
best. But
I suppose it works if you are 30 when
you get married.
Traveling with a with a partner is very
expensive. No question about that
because it's twice the expenses.
And then there's shopping and much more,
as we know.
Um
Look, if you want to do this, you you go
for it. You
you'll be free from your educational
loans by the time you're 28. Travel the
world for a couple of years, then get
married. I think it works.
You can make it work.
So, yeah.
Go for it. Go for it. All the best, sir.
All the best. Do well.
Um Shivansh says, "How to work with
incredibly political toxic boss?"
Ideally,
you quit. Move somewhere else. But
obviously, not everyone has that luxury.
That you know what, if my boss is
terrible, very toxic,
plays politics, I just walk out and find
another job. Maybe there's not um
there's a scarcity of jobs, perhaps. So,
then what do you do?
I don't know, man. I don't know.
I've also dealt with toxic bosses.
The best thing you do is move out.
Because a boss is a person who is in a
position of more power than you.
So, either you outmaneuver them
politically and get them sidelined them
if you are good at politics, or you seek
a better working environment.
So, that may not happen immediately. So,
maybe for a while you will deal with it.
The the ideal situation is you move
elsewhere. That's what I can tell you.
Uh Shivansh says, "What do you think
about the Escatian
hypothesis?" I don't know what that is.
What is that? Let me quickly take a
look.
Escatian Escatian hypothesis
hypothesis
What is that?
The first confirmed detection of an
extraterrestrial technological
civilization is most likely to be an
atypical example,
one that's um
you know, like um
Escatian hypothesis. I haven't read this
yet. Let me take a look at this.
The history of
rather
Okay, I am not aware of this. I think
it's reasonably interesting.
Let me see the PDF. Let me download
that, and I shall read it read it
at my
convenience. Thank you for
pointing this out. I don't know what
about what it's about because I haven't
read it, but I will check it out. Thank
you, sir.
Uh Deva 72,000 says, "How can a think
tank be built to foster long-term
economic and foreign policy thinking to
develop
and and develop high-quality alumni who
advance India's development regardless
of the ruling government?" For a think
tank, first of all,
you need to have money because you want
to employ people who will work in the
think tank and produce original
thinking.
So, you need some money.
Then you need to hire the right people.
People who have high-quality original
ideas.
So, you need money, then you need to
seek out and identify the right people.
Then they have to be willing to work for
you for whatever money you are providing
them.
Then you need leadership to tell them
what to do.
You need leadership, you need a
direction. The leadership needs to come
from a person who understands the world,
understands the issues, understands the
problems that India is facing
and can align everybody in the direction
that will be beneficial for India.
Then
you need a place where all this can be
all this work can be published. So you
have the you have the right leadership,
one person or maybe a committee of
people. Then you have
the money.
Then you have
the right people who are working for
you. Let's say 10 people, five people
also we can start with this can even
start a think tank with three people,
five people, whatever.
And work on a set of issues.
Then you have to give them guidance
about what kind of you know research to
do, what things to work on and in what
form the output should be. It should be
ideally you tackle a problem, you
identify what the problem is, what are
the root causes, what are the
consequences, how is it hurting the
country, how can it be resolved and you
give recommendations.
And then the think tank should be able
to reach out to the leadership. But here
is the problem, here are the problems,
here are the here are the problems, here
are the recommendations, here are the
here are the solutions.
Now you need to implement that. So you
need to be able to reach out otherwise
you you you just publishing stuff but
nobody's reading it.
So all of that needs to happen, you
know, that's how a think tank is built.
Sometimes some people build think tanks
to
to cater to other audiences, maybe not
for the government, maybe not maybe for
other corporate masters or something. So
you know, there are various kinds of
think tanks.
Would you like me to create a think
tank?
>> [laughter]
>> All right.
Sid Barka says, can ChatGPT put an end
to Indian entrance exams and tuition
coaching mafia? I'm preparing for GMAT
using it and surprised it answers all
questions correctly and explains
concepts really well for quant quant
quantitative stuff. Uh chat G G GPT, I
suspect it will do really well.
Uh I'm sure it doesn't cost a lot of
money.
And I it will definitely cost less than
the tuition coaching mafia, right?
So all you have to do is you you have to
I think input
the the course material.
So let's say
I don't know.
The I suppose everybody has PDF versions
of course course material these days.
You have to just give it to ChatGPT and
tell it, you know, this chapter explain
to me step-by-step.
All the
first section of of the chapter explain
it to me
in a way that I can understand the
easiest way.
And then you can ask it to to coach you
through it and you can ask it to to test
you. And then you can give of the past 5
10 years sample question papers and ask
it to
to to to to test you on that. So I
suppose you can replace all your tutors
etc. with ChatGPT.
I
It's definitely possible that ChatGPT
can replace all your
tutors, all your coaching mafia etc.
The thing about tutor is that you know
when you have ChatGPT you are
self-motivated.
So you have to make sure that you study
a certain amount of hours every day. But
when you have a tutor who
you go to
then
then that that much study is done and
that's it's a little more automatic. So
pros and cons but ChatGPT can definitely
replace any tutor
today.
Abhirup Sarkar says, any suggestions for
overthinking? I don't see it bad enough
from introspect I don't see
don't see it bad though from
introspection and unlearning perspective
especially coming from a troubled
childhood. Suggestions for overthinking.
Well
look first of all I'll tell you I'll
tell you that I
am not somebody who overthinks.
So it's not something if I tell you
something, if I give you some kind of
recommendation, it's not from personal
experience. I don't overthink.
Or maybe I
What is overthinking?
I think constantly.
My mind is always working, it's always
thinking something or the other.
But it doesn't harm me, hurt me or
burden me or anything.
I think
I think every human brain works all the
time, right? You're always thinking
something or the other.
But for some people it becomes problem
it becomes a burden
when maybe you have negative thought
patterns or something.
So
if you have positive thought patterns,
it's not going to hurt you, harm you at
all ever ever. But if your thought
patterns are negative
you're focusing on things you can't
control all the time, you think about
the same thing in a loop over and over
again. So that it's it's not the fact
that you're thinking all the time is the
fact that your thought patterns are
negative and harmful.
So that is when it becomes a burden on
you.
So my suggestion would probably be I
mean you should actually consult a
professional for this but I am suspect
my I suspect that overthinking is
actually
negative and and harmful thought
patterns that don't give you any
benefits but have lots of drawbacks and
and cause more trouble than they do good
for you. So you have to break out of
those thought patterns and replace them
with with more constructive and better
thought patterns that will actually be
beneficial for you. That's what I can
what I imagine. It's not a problem
that's it's never been a problem for me.
But yeah, so I am not an expert on this
matter, okay? So
this is just me thinking aloud right
now.
But I'm sure there are experts who can
coach you through how to
recover from overthinking or from
negative and harmful and and non-helpful
thought patterns. I suppose there could
be YouTube videos also about that or
maybe articles about that. So I would
say you should actually look into those
things.
Uh
take advice from people who actually are
professionals or people who have
successfully
solved this problem for themselves. I
probably am not the right person to ask
this because I've never had this issue.
Anyway, all the best to you, sir. Do
well and and I hope that you are able to
solve this issue.
And this is the last question for today,
it looks like. Okay.
Shivansh says, any reason why India has
one of the worst cultures in the world?
Look the culture comes from the
leadership.
The culture comes from the leadership.
In the West, what do we have?
In the US
companies are geared for success, for
competition,
for quick execution.
And especially in in in tech companies
you invest a lot in R&D, you invest a
lot
in long-term success.
Look at the AI companies etc.
Look at
how much they are reinvesting
into R&D.
In India, when a company does well, they
give dividends to their shareholders.
Right?
So in India there's no focus on R&D,
there is no focus on
creating real long-term value. There is
there is focus in for example in the
Indian IT sector on arbitrage the
arbitrage is model.
That in the US one hour of of software
work costs let's say $100. But in India
I can do the same one hour of software
work from one person in in $20. I can I
can I can pay my employee
a fraction of that and I will charge the
US company $20 per hour.
And I'll pay my guy maybe $5 an hour.
So I'm making 15 rupees $15
over here and and I'm charging something
else to the to the Americans. So I can
make a lot of money through this through
arbitrage. But you're not creating any
any real value, you're just just
providing a service.
So there are all these harmful
there are all these
you know, legacy issues and and and
there's no culture of excellence.
There's there's over-management, too
much management. Each company has
different issues. But overall in India
the focus has always been on on on all
these
these these these models, you know,
arbitrage and all that.
It's a
there's no culture of excellence,
unfortunately. And
much of this comes go goes back to the
education system.
In the Indian education system a good
student is one who is obedient and who
is like a parrot who can parrot
everything teachers teacher tells them.
And uh
once again there is no merit in so much
more. So all of that
you know, percolates down into the
corporate culture also.
And when the corporate leadership
tolerates toxic bosses, toxic managers
and all
then the whole culture permeates the
company. There's too much
reliance on HR.
I would say all all the non-performing,
non-working staff should be cut down to
the the
you know, smallest possible number.
But that's how it is. That's that's the
kind of culture you have in India. In
startups I think
the culture is better because startups
startups ideally have to sink or swim.
Of course when become unicorns without
actually breaking a profit that's again
going to be an issue. So there's So
India is is going through the growing
pains.
And
hopefully things improve. Yeah, okay.
All the best.
Uh VSVS again has gifted five more
memberships. Thank you so much, sir. You
are on a spree today. And also
yesterday. So thank you so much. I
really appreciate that.
And Arnav says, I'm about to give my JEE
exam. Which college I should prefer to
actually learn great engineering like
IIT and bits? Please suggest good
branch. I don't know anything.
I have no idea which are the good IITs.
I don't know which are the good
colleges. I am not in touch with the
details and intricacy intricacies of the
Indian education system.
I
I may be perhaps you could classify me
as an educator educationist whatever.
But I operate outside the Indian
education system. I have no idea which
college is good.
In the past certain IITs used to be
good. I have no idea how they are today.
I don't hear very good things about
them. So I am not the right person to
ask this.
I don't know.
Which branch? I don't even know what
branches are offered today.
So I don't know. I'm very sorry but I am
not the right person to ask these
questions.
You'll have to look at look at ask ask
somebody else. So sorry.
All the best sir. Do well.
Crack your JEE and and find the best
possible college or IIT to go into and
do well in life sir. All the best Arnav.
Arnav.
And that brings me to the end of today's
live stream. It's been almost close to 4
hours.
Okay. So thank you so much everybody. I
really appreciate all of you all your
questions. It's incredible the kind of
questions I get week after week. Very
interesting new questions as well.
So thank you so much everybody and I
look forward to taking more questions
from from you in next week's live
streams. Until then
take care.
Keep learning keep keep asking
questions. Keep raising your standards
and I will see you very soon in the next
live streams. Take care everyone.
Over and out for today. See you next
week. Bye.